<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sword-man's vade-mecum: or, A preservative against the surprize of a sudden attack with sharps Being a reduction of the most essential, necessary and practical part of fencing, into a few special rules, with their reasons, which all sword-men should have in their memories when they are to engage, but more especially if it be with sharps. As also, some other remarks and observations not unfit to be known by fencing masters and others. By Sir William Hope, kt. Author of the Compleat fencing-master.</title>
            <author>Hope, William, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827241</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1889:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sword-man's vade-mecum: or, A preservative against the surprize of a sudden attack with sharps Being a reduction of the most essential, necessary and practical part of fencing, into a few special rules, with their reasons, which all sword-men should have in their memories when they are to engage, but more especially if it be with sharps. As also, some other remarks and observations not unfit to be known by fencing masters and others. By Sir William Hope, kt. Author of the Compleat fencing-master.</title>
                  <author>Hope, William, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 97, [3] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by J. Taylor at the Ship in St. Paul's Church-yard, and S. Holford at the Crown in the Pall-Mall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The sword-man's vade-mecum, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fencing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31657:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31657:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SWORD-MAN's <hi>Vade Mecum:</hi> Or, A PRESERVATIVE Againſt the SURPRIZE OF A Sudden Attack with Sharps.</p>
            <p>BEING A Reduction of the moſt Eſſential, Neceſſary and Practical Part of Fencing, into a few ſpecial Rules, with their Reaſons, which all Sword-men ſhould have in their Memories when they are to engage, but more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be with Sharps.</p>
            <p>As alſo, Some other Remarks and Obſervations not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to be known by Fencing Maſters and Others.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>WILLIAM HOPE,</hi> Kt. Author of the Compleat Fencing-Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Taylor</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, and <hi>S. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in the <hi>Pall-Mall,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31657:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31657:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL TRUE ARTISTS, OR Such who have a Real Reſpect for, and take Delight in the ART of FENCING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I Wrote my Book of <hi>Fenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Entituled <hi>The SCOTS Fencing-Maſter,</hi> I deſigned it ſhould ſerve both to inſtruct the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and be a help to Art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts; to inſtruct the Ignorant by giving them a true and particular Deſcription of the moſt common Leſſons taught in the <hi>Fencing Schools,</hi> that ſo by it they might come to underſtand both better and ſooner, the Leſſons which their Maſters were daily to Deſcrive and Teach them; And I am very confident I have not failed as to that, for I dare appeal to any who ever took the pains to peruſe it, if ever they met with a piece upon the ſame ſubject, either ſo plain, or exact in the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Leſſons, as it is.</p>
            <p>I deſigned alſo it ſhould be a help to Artiſts, in ſo far as that the looking it over, would bring to their
<pb facs="tcp:31657:3"/>minds ſuch Leſſons, as want of Practice for ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time might have worn out of their Memories, and alſo in reſpect that there is in it very good directions and Rules for their behaviour in practice againſt either Artiſts or Ignorants, both with Blunts and Sharps.</p>
            <p>But in that Book I gave only a bare Diſcriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Rules, without any of the Reaſons ſubjoyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to them upon which they were grounded, which om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion did probably make ſome Artiſts judge, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Rules were not ſo very infallible, but that as good might be put in their places; And which it is like hath alſo been the cauſe of their not having ſo good an Opinion of, and liking for them, as perhaps otherwiſe they would.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that I might both vindicate the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and infallibility of my Rules, by ſhowing that they are not grounded meerly upon my own Fancy, but upon the ſolid Foundations of Art and Reaſon, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie ſuch perſons by publiſhing the Reaſons upon which I ground them; As alſo, make my Rules more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious, and eaſier to be kept in their memories, I have in theſe following ſheets made an Abſtract of them, and have given the Reaſons, why I order ſuch and ſuch a thing in ſuch a Rule.</p>
            <p>And although I cannot deny, but a judicious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt may perhaps make uſe of ſome Rules of his own choiſe, or making, differing ſomewhat from mine, which may be very good, and have ſometimes as good effect againſt the particular Play of the Perſons he is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage againſt as mine could have; Yet I am confident
<pb facs="tcp:31657:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey can be no better than mine are, and that if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſerved mine exactly againſt that ſame Perſon, he would find them to have the very ſame effects with his own, and to be againſt all humors whatſoever generally the more ſecure and certain of the two.</p>
            <p>But albeit I confeſs there may be particular Rules invented for particular humors of Play, which may differ from mine, and yet prove very effectual againſt that particular humor for which they were deſigned; yet againſt one of another humor they will be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ineffectual and prove ſtark nought, in which doth conſiſt their inſufficiency, whereas thoſe which I am to give you will not only prove as effectual againſt thoſe particular humors, as the particuar Rules deſigned for them, but will be ſufficient alſo againſt all humors whatſoever, ſo that there will be no need of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Ones, mine ſupplying their place becauſe they are general, in which doth lye their Worth and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
            <p>For to diſcover to you the unſufficiency of particular Rules, conſider but what difference there is betwixt a Man's playing with a Perſon whoſe humor and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of playing he knoweth, and with one whom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he never ſo much as ſaw before, certainly there muſt be Methods taken vaſtly diſſierent to play Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly againſt either of thoſe Perſons as a Man ſhall be engaged; for if he be Attaqued by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whoſe Play he knoweth, then knowing upon what Leſſons his humor runneth; I confeſs be may ſafely make uſe of particular Contrarys, and Purſuits which
<pb facs="tcp:31657:4"/>he knows will take effect upon his Adverſary, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though undoubtedly to uſe generalls were a great dale more ſafe) but if he be Attaqued by one whom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he never ſaw, or if he did, yet knoweth not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon what Leſsons his humor runneth: I ſay in ſuch a Caſe to make uſe of Particulars were but very bad Judgement.</p>
            <p>As for Example, to make a Real and Home Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite with a ſingle or double Feint, when no ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite will take effect upon that Perſon again whom he is playing, but what is accompanied with binding; or to take himſelf to any particular Parrade, when he is not certain what Leſſon his Adverſary is to play home upon him; this I ſay is but to play at Random, and wholly expoſe himſelf to Contretemps, by render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Art altogether Ineffectual.</p>
            <p>And this bad Cuſtom of uſing alwiſe Particulars, is certainly one of the main Reaſons, why the <hi>French</hi> (who are generally of a Brisk and Hot Conſtitution) are for the moſt part when they Engage either both Killed, or at leaſt ſeverly wounded, becauſe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after preſenting, they commonly Advance with the particular Purſuite of ſome ſingle or double Feint, without ever offering to ſecure their Adverſarie's Sword, and their Adverſary upon the other Hand, not being accuſtomed to a general Parrade, and finding he is not certain what particular one he ſhould make uſe of, endeavours to take time upon him, and ſo they are both wounded: This is the True <hi>French</hi> Play, whieh I confeſs hath a <hi>Bonne grace</hi> with it at
<pb facs="tcp:31657:4"/>Blunts, and appears Brisk and Couragious at Sharps; but as to its ſecurity, I leave that to be judged of by any conſidering Perſon, whither Artiſt or other.</p>
            <p>Therefore the only ſecure way is to make alwiſe uſe of Generalls againſt whatever Perſons you Play, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artiſts or not, until you have found out their Conſtitution and Humour, and what particular Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you judge will take effect upon them, and if you think it fit and convenient then to try Particulars, you may, but I would not adviſe you to do it ſooner if you regard your own ſafety.</p>
            <p>You may now perceive the great Advantage Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules have of Particular ones, and it is the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of thoſe General Rules that are of ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable uſe, which I am to ſet down to you together with their Reaſons in the following ſheets, but that there may want nothing to make them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and eaſie to be retained; I have alſo for your greater eaſe and ſatisfaction, (at the end of my Rules and before I give my Reaſons) Epitomized this Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, and brought it into ſo narrow a Compaſs, that a Man muſt have no memory at all, if he cannot ſo fix in his Fancy and Brain what I have there given him, as it ſhall not be in his power when he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth either Fleuret or Sword to get himſelf ridd of it.</p>
            <p>And it is upon that account I call it <hi>The SWORD-MAN</hi>'s <hi>Vade Mecum,</hi> not that I would have alwiſe theſe Sheets carried about with him in his Pocket; (for that any Ignorant can do as well as he, and be ne're a whitt the wiſer of them)
<pb facs="tcp:31657:5"/>but that the Epitome of my Rules which as I ſaid is at the end of them, may be ſo engraven in his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that when he is any wayes to Engage, he may through it practice all the reſt which are as it were lively repreſented in that Mirror, which muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe carried about with him, and ſtill repreſent thoſe Objects (I mean Directions) upon which his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt work.</p>
            <p>Now, as my former Book of Fencing was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the uſe both of Artiſts and Ignorants, ſo this Abſtract is only for Artiſts, there being only contained in it the very Marrow and Quinteſſence of Fencing, which without all debate is not only above the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all, but capacity of moſt part of Ignorants until it be explained to them, and therefore they can have no pretence or claime of Right to it; but if ſuch Perſons will be ſo courious as to take a look of it, its like they may find ſome things (in my Obſervations eſpecially) which may be a means to reclaime them, and make them ſenſible of their Ignorance and folly in contemning and neglecting an Art, by which a Man doth reap ſo many undenyable Advantages.</p>
            <p>And if the reading of this do it not; I aſſure them I ſhall not put my ſelf to to the trouble ſo much as to think of doing it any other way, having loſt all hopes that any thing will ſucced if this once fail; for to deal Ingenouſly, I am reſolved never to put Pen more to Paper upon this Subject, ſeing I think what I have ſaid firſt and laſt upon it, not only abundantly ſufficient to Inſtruct thoſe, whoſe gentile Inclinations do diſpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:31657:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem to take delight in, and follow this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Art; but alſo to convince and perſwade all who have the leaſt Drop of generous Blood, of the worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it.</p>
            <p>But leaving ſuch Perſons to follow their fooliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incliations, I do really acknowledge, that it is only to ſuch generous Spirits as you are (to whom I have Addreſsed theſe following Sheets) that I ſo earneſtly recomend the cloſs Practice and Obſervance of thir ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Rules, in the Rejecting or Approbation of which, I ſhall wholly ſubmit my ſelf to your Impartial Cencure; earneſtly Intreating, that if there ſhall be found any thing in them Repugnant to the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp; true Fundamentals of Art, I may be acquainted with it, that ſo I may either Vindicate my ſelf, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my Fault and Error; in both which I ſhall moſt willingly endeavour to ſatisfie all True Lovers of Art.</p>
            <p>And I aſſure you, were it not that I am Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, this Art (for which I have ſuch an Eſtime my ſelf, and of which I think I have given ſufficient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies) ſhould be both improven and be hereafter had in more Repute amongſt the generality of our Gentry then it hath been hitherto, I had never been either at the Trouble or Charges, to expoſe my ſelf a ſecond time to the ſenſure of the Publick, by giving you this (I may call it my <hi>Maſter-piece</hi> upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) in Print.</p>
            <p>I thought to have had the Approbation of moſt of the Maſters prefixed to this Piece; but there being
<pb facs="tcp:31657:6"/>ſome things in my Obſervations (eſpecially anent the Abuſes committed in <hi>Fencing-Schools</hi> to which I refer you) in which we differ, and which they would not go alongſt with, I have therefore only condeſcended to Print the Approbation of one who is of the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with my ſelf, which I hope will not be thought any Vanity in me, ſeing I am moſt ſenſible the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and Commendation he is pleaſed to beſtow u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, is far above what I really deſerve.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>ADIEU.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <head>A LETTER OF APPROBATION, BY WILLIAM MACHRIE <hi>FENCING-MASTER, Judge and Arbitrator of all who make any publick Trial of Skill in the Noble Art of the</hi> SWORD, <hi>within the Kindom of</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Papers, and have peruſed them ſo narrowly, that there is not one Paragraph or Line that has eſcaped my ſtricteſt Obſervation; wherein, I find nothing
<pb facs="tcp:31657:6"/>but Plain, Undenyable, and Inerrable Truths: And (without Complement) beyond any thing that ever I have Read on that Subject; all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors being ſo Abſtruſe and Intricate, that thoſe who have acquired a conſiderable knowledge of the Sword, cannot reach the underſtanding of their Writtings; ſo that in my Opinion, who ever may claime the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being the firſt Author of the Noble Art of Defence, I am confident there is none who reads what you have Writ on that Subject; but will readily Eeſteem you one of the moſt conſiderable Advancers of it, that any Age or Country hath yet produced.</p>
            <p>The Rules of Practice which you have ſo Clearly and Orderly ſet down in your <hi>SCOTS Fencing Maſter,</hi> ſhews you to be a great Maſter of the Art; and your reducing all theſe to ſo ſmall a number, together with the ſolid Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Demonſtrations you have given of them in your SWORD MAN'S <hi>Vade mecum,</hi> evidences you to be alſo in the Judgement of the Sword, a Maſter of all ARTISTS.</p>
            <p>Certainly the Sword was never ſo much Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depted to the Pen before, as it is now by that late Piece of yours, wherein you have done this conſiderable Honour to the Art, that as formerly (for want of Reaſons and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of its Rules) it was ſcarce accounted an Art, and but a <hi>Mechanical</hi> one at beſt; Now its Fundamental Rules being digeſted into
<pb facs="tcp:31657:7"/>good order, founded on firm Reaſons, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by ſolid Demonſtrations, it may juſtly claim all the <hi>priviledges,</hi> that any of the <hi>Liberal</hi> or <hi>Mathematical Arts</hi> can pretend to.</p>
            <p>Proceed then (Worthy Sir) in your Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deſign of improving the Noble Art of the Sword, which me-thinks does only wait, and hope to receive 'its outmoſt Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the Pen &amp; Hands of Sir WILLIAM HOPE. For your pains herein will Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly meet with the juſt Requitable of Praiſe, Honour and Eſteem, from all true Lovers of Armes and Arts; together alſo with all Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thanks, eſpecially from <hi>Sword-men;</hi> whom you cannot either Honour or Oblidge more, then by publiſhing that Piece; which merits more Applauſe and Commendation, then can ever be given it, by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOURABLE,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt Humble and Obedient Servant,</hi> William Machrie.</signed> 
               <dateline>Aberdeen, <date>
                     <hi>April,</hi> 30. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31657:7"/>
            <head>THE SWORD-MANS VADE MECUM, OR, <hi>A Preſervative againſt the Surprize, of a Sudden Attaque with Sharps, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EING to Direct my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Perſons ſo knowing and Skilful as You are to whom I have Addreſſed theſe Sheets; I think I need but ſay little (by way of Introduction) in Commendation of this ART, either to Diſplay its Excellencies, or Recommend it to You; the very Tittle of my Dedication ſuppoſing you to need nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, to excite You to its Practice.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore at preſent only ſay, that the Generous and Noble Art of Defence (paſſing by all its other Qualities) may in ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be compared to the moſt Excellent and moſt Sublime of all Sciencies, I mean that of <hi>Divinitie;</hi> For as Divinity doth teach us, <hi>to defend our Souls from the cruel aſſaults and attempts of that old Serpent the Devil, the cunning and ſubtile alure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31657:8"/>of the World, and theſe pleaſant and ſhort but deſtroving luſts of the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So doeth the <hi>Art of Fencing</hi> teach us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Bodies, from the Aſſaults and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques of all Adverſaries, whether Artiſts or not, who in reſpect of the cruel deſigne they have againſt our Bodies, may in ſome ſenſe be accounted Devils, it alſo teacheth us not to be deceived by the fallacious Quirks and Tricks of Artiſts when we are engaged with them, which do repreſent the cunning and ſubtile Allurements of the World.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, it furniſheth us with directions to defend our ſelves from the Thruſts and Wounds of our Adverſaries, which although they can be ſaid to be pleaſant to none but the Giver, yet are ſhort and deſtroying to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, ſhort and tranſitory, becauſe they are ſwift and given in the twinkling of an eye, or a moment; and deſtroying, becauſe they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom faile to diſſipate and give a Paſſage to our Vital Spirits; by which we are ſent a pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to our long Home: And therefore they may be juſtly compared becauſe of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſhort continuance) to the pleaſures of the World; and the Compariſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yet nearer, <hi>In ſo far as they reach not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Body, but ofttimes alſo endanger the Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seing then there is ſuch an Annallogie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this Humane Art and that Divine Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31657:8"/>what kind of Perſons muſt thoſe be who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndervallow it?—But when I reflect a little, find it no great ſurprizal that <hi>Fencing</hi> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet with ſo many Oppoſers and Contemners when even Divinity yea GOD Himſelf (to ſpeak with Reverence) is by ſome treated <hi>En Ridicule,</hi> and I am apt to believe that the diſpiſing and contempt of both, (although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here be no equality in the Compariſon) may flow from the ſame Original and Source.</p>
            <p>For as it is impoſſible for any Man who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of the whole, nay; but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>malleſt and moſt inconſiderable part of the Univerſe, to doubt of a firſt or ſupreme Beeing, until from the conſciouſneſs of his Sins &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, it become his Intereſt there ſhould be none; ſo is it Impoſſible for any Man who reflects upon, and conſiders the excellencies of <hi>Fencing,</hi> to doubt or queſtion the uſefulneſs of it; until from a ſence of his own Ignorance, and of the Advantadges he knows Artiſts will have over him; it doth become his Intereſt, that there ſhould be no ſuch thing as Art, or at leaſt that what is called Art ſhould be of no uſe: And this is certainly one of the chief Reaſons, why the Art of the Sword is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much undervalued, by thoſe who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it not.</p>
            <p>But that I may the better repreſent ſuch Perſons to you: conſider in what a Piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31657:9"/>and Deplorable condition they are, when (after having received a challenge, or being obliged to Fight in Rancounter) they ſeriouſly reflect upon the Art, and Androit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Antagoniſts, and their own <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droitneſs, &amp; Ignorance,</hi> by which they are rendred incapable of either knowing what way to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin their Purſuite, or defend themſelves; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly their thoughts at that time muſt either abaite and cool their Courage, or make them altogether deſperate.</p>
            <p>And indeed, to ſee the moſt part of them when they are engaged for their Lives, one would judge them to be by their Purſuits, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of their Witts, and Madd-men, then Sober and Rational Perſons; and they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate to force themſelves unto that Furie and Paſſion, that ſo their frowardneſs may ſomewhat ſupply their Ignorance; for if they declined to Fight, it would loſs them their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Honour; Therefore to ſave that they muſt Fight, and in Fighting it is odds but they loſs their Life, which to preſerve they uſe all the moſt unſeemly and deſperate Actions in the World; all which will not do againſt compleat Artiſts ſuch as you are.</p>
            <p>And if it be asked why Ignorants (for I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect they will not take it ill I give them this Diſignation, ſeing it is not done out of any Contempt to their Perſons, or reflection upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31657:9"/>their Judgements which may be very deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g in other things, but meerly becauſe it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cuſtom amongſt <hi>Swordmen,</hi> to let all who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>derſtand not the Art of the Sword go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Name) are generally more Subject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Paſſion and Forewardneſs in their Purſute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an <hi>Artiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, That in ſome Extremes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is a Coincidence, and that <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce</hi> may ſometimes act alike, as in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> for as Deſperation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich is the heigth of Fear, doth many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing ſharpned by Neceſſity) excite Courage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d beget Hope; ſo Temerity which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight of Courage, doth often (from expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of Danger) breed Caution, which is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cret Fear;</p>
            <p>Now to make the application, <hi>Ignorance</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om a ſenſe it hath of the Hazard and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er it may receive from Art, begets Fear or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpair, and being ſharpned up by this Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir which is as it were a leaven to make it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, it is forced and hoaved up (although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trary to its Nature) to Courage and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs which I may properly enough call, <hi>Temeritatis vel Ignorantiae audacia,</hi> and which ſhould be never eſteemed nor made uſe of, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt in a great Extreme or Neceſſity, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath its ariſe from <hi>Ignorance,</hi> which is the ground and cauſe of its being ſo frequently put
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31657:10"/>in practice by thoſe who have little or no Art and this I take to be the Reaſon of <hi>Ignorant</hi> having generally ſo hot and violent a Purſute</p>
            <p>So by this you may perceive how <hi>Ignorant</hi> may prompt a Man to be Forward and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious as well as Art: now as <hi>Ignorance</hi> (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Diametrically</hi> oppoſite to Art, and which ſhould in reaſon produce nothing but Fear and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern) doth excite Courage, ſo doth Art, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in reaſon ſhould be <hi>Prolifick</hi> of nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Courage and <hi>Heroick</hi> Actions, breed ſome times Caution, which may be very well calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a diſcreet and reaſonable Fear, or rather <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae &amp; experientiae Cautela,</hi> and which is only e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and put in practice by Judicious an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Underſtanding <hi>Artiſts,</hi> becauſe it proceed from the experience which Art giveth then of the danger they would run in making a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent and inconſiderate Purſute, which is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carried on with Judgement, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Art;</hi> and this is the Reaſon why <hi>Artiſt</hi> are generally not ſo <hi>foreward</hi> and <hi>irregular</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Purſutes as <hi>Ignorants,</hi> but more <hi>caution</hi> and <hi>ſlow,</hi> and conſequently more <hi>certain</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not therefore (from what I have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaying) far more commendable, to be <hi>dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous</hi> and <hi>regular</hi> in our <hi>Offenſive</hi> and <hi>Defenſive motions,</hi> then <hi>irregular,</hi> and as it were out of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:31657:10"/>Hope, and in Depair, that if we overcome, we may be ſaid to have done it by <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Judgement,</hi> and not at <hi>randome,</hi> and by <hi>chance,</hi> more beſeeming an <hi>irrational</hi> than a <hi>rational</hi> Creature.</p>
            <p>If it be, what <hi>Art</hi> can teach us better, than this of <hi>Fencing?</hi> I confeſs I need not recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to you, whoſe Inclinations have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy led you that way, but perhaps it may not prove an unſeaſonable Advice to others who may peruſe this &amp; the foregoing Dedication.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore ſay no more in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this Noble and <hi>Gentlemany</hi> Art, but ſhall before I proceed, ſhew you the Method I intend to follow in Communicating and Diſcovering the Reaſons upon which it is grounded, and the Source from whence all its Worth and Security doth flow; and for the more regular Procedure ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> give you the ſingle Rules, one after another, which you are alwayes to have in your Memory; Then <hi>ſecondly</hi> each particular Rule by it ſelf, with the Reaſons ſubjoyned to it upon which it is grounded; And <hi>thirdly,</hi> ſome Remarkes and Obſervations, all which will be both Uſeful, and if I miſtake it not, pleaſant to the Reader.</p>
            <div n="1" type="rules">
               <head>Firſt, The R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LES.</head>
               <p>BEfore I begin, I ſhall give you a <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> which in reſpect of its Excellency, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31657:11"/>Univerſality, I may call the <hi>Golden Number,</hi> or <hi>Rule of Three,</hi> both becauſe it is alwayes to be taken alongſt with you, and to be made a part, (and that none of the leaſt) of each Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Rule I am to give you, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conſiſts of Three important Terms or Words, which are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calmneſs,—Vigour,</hi>—and <hi>Judgement</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe three Words in general, being the only Foundation upon which all Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Fencing</hi> is built, and each Word in particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being as it were a Column, or Pillar by which my Rules are to be ſupported, (for without them all would be but Uncertain and Falſe I ſhall begin my Firſt Rule, which as well as all the reſt, is to be ſupported by thoſe three in fallible, and never to be too exactly copie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pillars of the compoſite Order, becauſe each of them in ſome meaſure partake of the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Excellency of the other two, and to that end Earneſtly and Seriouſly intreats and deſires: That.</p>
               <div n="1" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whatever you do, let it alwayes (if poſſible) be done Calmely, and without Paſſion, and Precipitation, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſtill with all</hi> Vigour, <hi>and Briskneſs imaginable your</hi> Judgement <hi>not failing to Direct, Order, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Govern you as to both.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="rule">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:31657:11"/>
                  <head>RULE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>put your ſelf into as Cloſs, Thinn, and Convenient a Guard, as the Agility of your Body will permit, your Heels being ſtill kept as near other as poſſible.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>make uſe (for your Defence) of the moſt Excellent, and not to be parrallelled</hi> Contre-caveating <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, and that generally upon the outſide of your Sword, your left hand alwayes aſiſting you if any wayes doubtful of the Parrade; and that you may with the more certainty defend your ſelf, look alwayes to your Adverſary's Sword-Hand.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>IIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>endeavour to Offend your Adverſary, by binding or ſecuring his Sword, and that for the moſt part alſo upon the outſide, giving in a ſingle plain Thruſt upon the back of it, or if you pleaſe make a Feint upon the back of your Binding, your left Hand making alwayes a kind of Parrade, at the giving in of every Thruſt, the better to ſave you from a</hi> Contre-temps; <hi>and by no means reſt upon your Thruſt, but inſtantly after the performing of it, whether you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itt or not, recover to your Defenſive Poſture again: This is the true Play for a Mans Life: but if you be ſo far Maſter of your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31657:12"/>Adverſary, and ſo merciful to him that you deſign not his Life, but only to diſable him: Then.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>Thruſt at his Sword-hand, Wreſt, or Arm, or at his neareſt advanced Thigh, the wounding any of which once, or twice, will ſeldome fail to diſable him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If your Adverſary be Haſty, Paſſionate, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Furiouſly, and Irregulaty, then with</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>Croſs, Stop, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Fury: but upon the contrary if Careleſs, Laſh, Slow, or perhaps Timerous, then alſo</hi> Calmly, Vigorouſly, <hi>and with</hi> Judgement <hi>purſue him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>prevent your Receiving one Thruſt for the giving ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, called (after that dangerous Word, and</hi> Artiſts Bug bear) <hi>a</hi> Contre-temps, <hi>and for that end the uſing your left Hand for a</hi> Defence <hi>upon your Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute, as I have before told you, will not be found amiſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now to put a Cloſe to my</hi> Rules, <hi>let them all be done within diſtance as much as poſſible, and with little or no</hi> Elonge, <hi>or ſtretch of any part of the Body, ſave only that of the Wreſt &amp; Arm (called a</hi> Spring) <hi>and as I deſired you to begin, ſo I expect you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31657:12"/>and end all your Actions, with that moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Fundamental, and</hi> Golden Rule of Three, <hi>to wit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calmneſs,—Vigour,</hi>—and <hi>Judgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And then no doubt, you will procure by the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Rules, <hi>advantage proportionable to the Art you have acquired to put them in practice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that my Reduction may yet better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my Deſign, (which was to be ſhort and compendious) and be more eaſily kept in your Memory, I have brought it into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower Compaſs, by, as it were Epitomizing it as followeth.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>With Calmneſs Vigour, and Judgement</head>
                     <item>Uſe
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A Cloſs Guard.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>The Contre-caveating-Parrade.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Binding.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A Contretemps.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Being without Diſtance.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Reſting upon a Thruſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>A Man muſt be certainly void both of Art and Memory, if upon all neceſſary Occaſions he cannot furniſh himſelf, with ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Preſervative as this; but ſeing the very doubting of it, would be ſo abſurd, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much a Mans <hi>Ignorance</hi> and weakneſs, I ſhall ſay no more, but (deſiring to leave it as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31657:13"/>it were Ingraven in your Memory) procee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the ſecond thing I propoſed, which was.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="explication_of_rules">
               <head>Secondly.</head>
               <p>Each particular Rule, with the Reaſon ſubjoined to it, upon which it is Grounded.</p>
               <div n="1" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Whatever you do, let it alwayes (if poſſible,) b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> done</hi> Calmely, <hi>and without Paſſion, and Preci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation:</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I find by Experience that Paſſion expoſeth a Man, and incapacitates him, from making uſe of his Art with that Diſcretion which is required of him, to procure the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable Advantage he hath by it.</p>
                  <p>But that he may not by being adviſed to Play <hi>Calmly,</hi> fall into the other Extreme of Playing too Careleſly, Laſhly, and perhaps Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſly, (it being difficult to determine which of theſe two Extremes, do moſt Eclipſe a Mans Art, and conſequently moſt expoſe him to his Adverſaries mercy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he is adviſed to counterfeit a kind of Paſſion, by playing Briskly, and Vigourouſly, it being as it were a <hi>Medium,</hi> or if I may ſo call it a <hi>Ballance</hi> or <hi>Counterpoiſe,</hi> which upon the one Hand prevents his ſinking in the Gulf of Unreaſonable, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31657:13"/>Unmanly Fear, which would loſs him his Reputation, and Honour, dearer to a Man than his very Life, and upon the other his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending the Ragged, Unequal, and Diſperate Rock of inconſiderate Paſſion and Forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for which there is oftentimes hardly any Retreat, or Deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent, but by the Life of a Mans Adverſary, if no his own with it, both which ſhould be preſerved as much as poſſible, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, not only of the great in it is againſt <hi>God Almighty</hi> (which to all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Reaſon) but alſo in reſpect of the ſevere puniſhments the Laws both of <hi>God</hi> &amp; Man, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain to be inflicted upon ſuch as are guilty of either: And for effectuating of which, if I be not deceived this firſt Rule will not a little contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ute, if it be practiſed cautiouſly &amp; as I have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the end of it, with <hi>Judgement,</hi> without which the beſt Rule I can give or invent to you, will not ſignifie a Straw, it being ſuch a chief Ingredient, that without it all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions both for <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Offence,</hi> in our <hi>Fencing Pharmacopie</hi> would ſignifie but little or nothing, as I ſhall more fully hereafter declare, when I ſpeak to the Eight Rule.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut your ſelf into as Gloſs, Thinn, and convenient a Guard,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:31657:14"/>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe it is moſt certain, that the cloſer a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſink to the Ground, the more ſecure he is from all the Thruſts which may be given in beneath his Sword at the lower parts of his Body, which without all manner of doubt are both very dangerous, and moſt difficult to Defend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Parrades</hi> of them lie not ſo Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a Man's Hand (ſuppoſing him to ſtand to a <hi>High Guard</hi>) as the <hi>Parrades</hi> of the Thruſt given in above, and that either without the Sword or within it.</p>
                  <p>And the Reaſon is, becauſe in the <hi>Defenſiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> part of the ſmal Sword, all the <hi>Parrades</hi> that are made beneath the Hand are a great dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtronger and firmer, becauſe they are, and ought to be done with a <hi>Jerk</hi> or <hi>Spring,</hi> whereas all the <hi>Parrades</hi> of the Thruſts below the Sword, ſuch as that of <hi>Feint a la teſte, Volt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coupee, Flancanade, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder counter,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be all (ſuppoſing him to ſtand to a <hi>High Guard</hi>) parried Slopwayes, &amp; your Adverſaries Sword born off, and a little up, as it were, by yours, which both hindereth the <hi>Spring</hi> and weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Parrade,</hi> by reaſon of the compelled Poſture and Diſpoſition of your Hand, both which Inconveniences are abſolutely Guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt and ſhunned, by ſinking cloſs to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31657:14"/>Ground, and keeping the Hilt of your Sword little higher than your Knee, and the point little higher than your Hilt, becauſe this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re prevents the playing of any of the above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entioned low Thruſts upon you.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, I order a thinn Guard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cauſe it would be to no purpoſe to ſink cloſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d endeavour by it to cover one part of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ody, to wit that beneath your Sword, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſame time you diſcover your left Side, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt of your Body, which as much if not more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſerves to be ſecured, becauſe in it is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, one of the moſt Noble, and (if wounded) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt Mortal parts of a Man's Body, I mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Heart.</p>
                  <p>Beſides reaſon will teach a Man, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould make himſelf as little a mark for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>verſary to thruſt at as poſſible, and I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> better Method to do that, than by ſinking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſs to the Ground, and keeping back your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eft ſhoulder or ſide, the one which is ſinking, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aking your Body ſhorter, and the other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich is keeping back your Left Side, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Body thinner, which two anſwer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o things required by common and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll Reaſon, <hi>viz. The making a Mans Body as ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d narrow a Mark for his Adverſary to Thruſt at, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſible.</hi> I confeſs this Poſture of ſinking ſo cloſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Ground, is a little Uneaſie at firſt to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31657:15"/>acquired by thoſe who have not been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to it, but a little Practice in this, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all other things, will make it become in a ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time as Familiar and Eaſie, as any other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; therefore let not its Uneaſineſs at fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſcourage any perſon from atempting to lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it, for the advantage he will reap by it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, will ſufficiently Recompence the Pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Trouble he was at to make himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it.</p>
                  <p>In the third Place, I order a convenien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Guard, ſuch as the Agility of your Body wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> permit, and by that I mean, that although have ordered ſinking to the Ground, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Thinn Body; yet rather than that a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould (by not having that Agility of the Body and Practice requiſite to perform that Poſture force and conſtrain himſelf into a Guard which would be uneaſie to him, by reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his endeavouring to obey exactly my Rule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> am rather ſatisfied that he ſink but ſo much and keep ſo thinn a Body as he findeth himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt firm in, and from which he is moſt abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to defend himſelf, and Purſue his Adverſary although it be not exactly according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt Directions I gave him.</p>
                  <p>And the Reaſon for which I allow him thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Latitude, is becauſe I find all conſtrained Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtures, weaken both a Man's Defence and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31657:15"/>and I had rather have a Man Play from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Poſture wherein he can uſe his <hi>Vigour,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hough it be not altogether ſo ſecure and cloſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s I could wiſh it, than ſee him play Feeblely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Feintly from a Poſture, for which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath not had Practice enough to make it Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and Eaſie, even although that Poſture) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſpect of another Perſons Agility, may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound to be the more ſafe, and ſecure Poſture of the two, becauſe of its cloſneſs, but which cannot be ſo to him, by reaſon of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint it putteth upon him.</p>
                  <p>But I give not this Allowance to make a Man negligent in acuſtoming himſelf to a cloſs and thinn Guard, not at all, it is only granted to him upon Neceſſity and for a time, until he hath had ſo much Practice as to make it Familiar, and Eaſie to his Body, which the ſooner it be, ſo much the better, therefore by no means ſpare either Pains or Labour to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it.</p>
                  <p>The Fourth thing I order is, That your Heels be ſtill as near other as poſſible, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the Reaſon I have for this will come more properly in, when I ſpeak to the Eight Rule, I ſhall forbear the ſetting it down till then, and at preſent proceed to my Third Rule which is.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="rule">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:31657:16"/>
                  <head>RULE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>make uſe (for your Defence) of the moſt Excelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and not to be parallelled</hi> Contre-caveating Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rade: <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I find the <hi>Contre-caveating</hi> Parra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be ſo ſafe and general a <hi>Parrade,</hi> that a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> who can rightly make uſe of it, needeth almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no other, for whereas to ſeveral of the <hi>Leſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> you muſt uſe proper and particular <hi>Parrade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſuch as are the <hi>Parrades</hi> which are in a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Peculiar to <hi>Feint a la Teſt, Volt-coupee, Fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> canade: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndercounter,</hi> &amp;c: If you make uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Contre caveating</hi> Parrade, you ſave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Trouble of chooſing a particular <hi>Parrade,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alſo, the running the hazard of being ſurpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Quick-handed Adverſary, (who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can well think upon what <hi>Parrade</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> moſt proper to Defend the <hi>Leſſon</hi> you imagin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he is going to Play, would have the Thru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> home at you) but making uſe of this <hi>Parra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> exactly, you will certainly have your deſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Defending your ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Beſides in making uſe of other <hi>Parrades <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> man</hi> may be deceived, by reaſon of his judgin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that the thruſt will be given within the Swor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31657:16"/>when it is really deſigned to be given without, or without the Sword when it is really to be given within, ſo that although a Man have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quick enough <hi>Parrade,</hi> and a good Eye; yet you ſee he may be deceived with other <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ades</hi> becauſe of his wrong judging of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng in of the Thruſt, but making uſe of this <hi>Parrade</hi> as he ſhould, he will never be deceived, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or this <hi>Parrade</hi> Croſſeth and Confoundeth the whole Art of the Sword, as <hi>Binding, Slipping, Plain thruſts, ſingle and double Feints of all kinds, Quarting, Volting,</hi> &amp;c. which cannot be ſaid of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny other particular <hi>Parrade</hi> of the Sword, but of this moſt Excellent <hi>Contre caveating Parrade.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Reaſon is, becauſe it is a Circular <hi>Parrade</hi> including a whole Circle, whereas the other <hi>Parrades</hi> make but a Part of a Circle, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſo much as they come ſhort of the whole Circle, in ſo far are they Defective and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, becauſe the Thruſt may come in at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat part of the Circle, which the Parrade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>whatever one it be) left Uncloſed or Unfini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hed, and therefore the ſecond <hi>Parrades</hi> in <hi>Quart</hi> and <hi>Terce</hi> with a Slooping Point, are more ſecure and certain, although not ſo quick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd firm, as the firſt <hi>Parrades</hi> in <hi>Quart</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erce</hi> with the Point a little higher than the <hi>Hilt,</hi> &amp; that becauſe theſe make more of a Circle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han thir do, but this <hi>Contre-caveating Parrade</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:31657:17"/>is a great deal more Secure then either of them for it maketh not only one whole Circle, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſometimes two or three, which is the reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> its ſo infallibly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeling and Engaging the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Sword, and conſequently of its bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo Infallible a <hi>Parrade.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Second place, I order it to be uſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> generaly upon the outſide, and my Reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for that is, becauſe firſt it diſordereth a Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Adverſaries <hi>Sword-hand</hi> much more to <hi>Parri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Bind</hi> or <hi>Secure</hi> him upon the Outſide of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sword, all which this <hi>Parrade</hi> doth, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Parr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, Bind</hi> or <hi>Secure,</hi> him upon the inſide, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that becauſe when you <hi>Parrie</hi> or <hi>Bind</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Natural Poſture of his hand Facilitats bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his redoubling of a thruſt upon you, if he deſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it, and his ſlipping you when you are goin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Bind</hi> him, which is juſt contrary when yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Offer to <hi>Parrie</hi> or <hi>Bind</hi> him with out, for the the diſpoſition of his hand is ſo forced out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eaſie, and natural Situation of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that it rende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him, if not uncapable, yet at leſt a great dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſlower both in his redoubling, &amp; ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pping. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this is the Advantage you will reap by <hi>Parri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> with the <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tre caveating Parrade</hi> upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out Side of your Adverſaries Sword.</p>
                  <p>There is yet another conſiderable Advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which a Man may have by uſing this <hi>Parrad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and it is this, if it ſhould be a Mans fortune <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be Engaged in the dark, all the <hi>Parrades</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:31657:17"/>World will never ſo find out, Engage, and Secure his Adverſary's ſword as this will, for if a Mans Sword came in the Dark, but within the Reach of yours, it will be impoſſible for you but you muſt feel it, becauſe of the Reaſons above mentioned, which will be a means to Secure you from the uncertain <hi>Attaeque</hi> of your Adverſary, and alſo make you more certain of what you are to do your Self, even al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be in the Dark, which is an Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that no other <hi>Parrade</hi> will yeild you but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, and therefore in my humble opinion not to be neglected or undervalued.</p>
                  <p>The Third-thing that I ordered, was that your left hand ſhould alwayes aſſiſt you, if you were any wayes doubtfull of the <hi>Parrade,</hi> and indeed this is ſo neceſſary a thing, eſpecialy in the <hi>Offenſive</hi> part, that what I intend moſtly to ſay of it, I ſhall refer to my diſcourſe upon the next <hi>Rule,</hi> (being on <hi>Offenſive</hi> one) and at preſent ſhall only ſay, when the <hi>Contre caveating Parrade</hi> requireth the uſe of the left Hand to ſupply its wants, with what Confidence can the other <hi>Parrades</hi> claim the Name they have, ſeing they are ſo deficient (in reſpect of it) to give a Man that Satisfaction and Security, which but juſtly he ſhould expect, for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Pains he hath been at, to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, Learn, and put them in Practice.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31657:18"/>
                  <p>But not to be tedious the laſt thing <hi>I</hi> order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was, that to Defend your ſelf with the more certainty, you ſhould look always to your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Sword-hand, and the Reaſon of this is, becauſe if you ſhould endeavour to draw any obſervation from his eyes, he may deceive you by looking in your Face, when he intends to thruſt at your Belly, or looking at your Belly when he intends to thruſt you in the Face, or if it ſhould ſo fall out that your Adverſary Squint, it is in that caſe impoſſible for you by looking to ſuch a Perſons Eyes, to Conjecture where, and at what Part of your Body, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to thruſt.</p>
                  <p>Neither will a Man though his Adverſary have a ſtraight look perceive it well, or be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether certain uponwhat part of his Body th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thruſt is comming in, by even looking to the Swords blade, firſt by Reaſon of its clearneſs which in a manner dazelleth a Mans Eyes with the motion it maketh; Secondly by Reaſon of the ſwiftneſs of its motion, which is a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deal ſwifter then that of his hand, for his hand being the <hi>Center,</hi> and the <hi>Swords point</hi> the <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> and the <hi>Sword</hi> as it were a Line <hi>Draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> from that <hi>Circumference</hi> to the hand or <hi>center,</hi> to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which it is in a manner fixed, it will by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Mathematicall demonſtration</hi> follow, that all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Parts of the <hi>Sword</hi> from the Hand to the Poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:31657:18"/>make proportionably a <hi>Swifter motion</hi> then the Hand doth, as they are diſtant from it, and do <hi>nearer approach</hi> to the Point or <hi>Circumference:</hi> A <hi>true Simile</hi> of which is a <hi>Wheel,</hi> the <hi>Neave</hi> or <hi>Center</hi> of which Repreſenteth the <hi>Hand,</hi> the <hi>Spoaks</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>Rimm,</hi> or <hi>outmoſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>umference</hi> the <hi>Swords</hi> Point; Now ſet the <hi>Wheel</hi> in Motion by turning it about, and you ſhall perceive pretty diſtinctly the <hi>Spoaks</hi> in their Motion at the <hi>Center</hi> as they are turning, but you ſhall not at all perceive them in their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion at the <hi>Rimm</hi> or <hi>outmoſt Circumference,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Swiftneſs</hi> of their Motion; it is juſt ſo with the Motion of a <hi>Sword</hi> at the <hi>Hilt</hi> and <hi>Point.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that, to look to the middle of a <hi>Swords Blade,</hi> or within a Foot of its <hi>Hilt,</hi> is not ſo certain as to look to its <hi>Hilt,</hi> becauſe the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Sword,</hi> at that Foots diſtance from the <hi>Hilt,</hi> or at the middle of it, is a great deal quicker, than the Motion at the <hi>Hilt,</hi> which as it was ſaid before, is as it were the <hi>Center,</hi> and therefore the ſloweſt Mover, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y the ſafeſt to look to; but to look to the <hi>Swords</hi> Point, which is the <hi>outmoſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erence,</hi> is yet worſt of all, for it being double the Diſtance from the <hi>Center,</hi> or <hi>Hilt,</hi> that the middle of the <hi>Sword</hi> is, and every part of the <hi>Sword</hi> moving in proportion Swiftlier, as they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31657:19"/>are farther diſtant from the <hi>Center,</hi> it will by Demonſtration follow, that the Motion of the <hi>Sword</hi> at the Point, exceeds the Motion of it at the <hi>Middle,</hi> as much as the Motion at the <hi>Middle,</hi> exceeds the Motion at the <hi>Center,</hi> or <hi>Hilt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, to look to the <hi>Point,</hi> or <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> that ſo a Man may be certain of its Motion, is Ridiculous, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, by reaſon of its being the Swifreſt <hi>Mover;</hi> and to look to the <hi>Middle</hi> part of the <hi>Sword,</hi> although I confeſs it to be more certain than to look to the <hi>Point,</hi> yet it is alſo not at all to be Truſted to, by reaſon that its Motion is too quick, but to look (according to my Direction) to the <hi>Sword-hand,</hi> or <hi>Center,</hi> is a thing moſt certain, and only to be Truſted to, (and that becauſe of its ſlow Motion) for the better perceiving the Motion of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and finding out where a Man intends to Thruſt, as I think I have fully Demonſtrate, and with out the Obſervation of which, a Man can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with Confidence, and Aſſurance ſay, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he either is, or can be, Maſter of the <hi>Parrade.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>IV.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>endeavour to Offend your Adverſary, by</hi> Binding, <hi>or</hi> Securing <hi>his</hi> Sword, <hi>and that for the moſt part,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:31657:19"/>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe it is found that <hi>Binding,</hi> or <hi>Securing</hi> ones Adverſaries <hi>Sword,</hi> before a Man offer to give home any Thruſt, (his left Hand mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes a kind of <hi>Parrade</hi> at the giving in of every Thruſt) is the only Safe and Secure Play, with either <hi>Blunts</hi> or <hi>Sharpes;</hi> to ſecure a Man from <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſts,</hi> which I ſhall endeavour to prove.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe you intend but to Play a plain Thruſt upon your Adverſary, then unleſs you firſt Secure his <hi>Sword,</hi> by beating it out of the way, you muſt certainly Thruſt ſtraight home, without ſo much as regarding his <hi>Swords</hi> being juſt oppoſite to, and preſented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and in that Caſe, what ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him to Thruſt juſt as you are Thruſting, and to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> with you?</p>
                  <p>You will perhaps ſay, your Thruſting cloſs by the Feeble of his <hi>Sword,</hi> will bear off his Thruſt, or the <hi>quarting</hi> of your Head and Shoulders well will ſave it; but do not deceive your ſelf with this fancie; for in the firſt place I can aſſure you, that although when you play upon a Maſters Breaſt, he may ſuffer you to Thruſt alwayes cloſs to his <hi>Sword,</hi> yet in Practice it will not be in your power once in ſix Thruſts, to have the opportunity of thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31657:20"/>cloſs to your Adverſaries <hi>Sword,</hi> and ſo that will not hold. But ſecondly, ſuppoſe you ſhould Thruſt cloſs to your Adverſaries <hi>Sword,</hi> and <hi>quart</hi> your Head and Shoulders well, what doeth hinder your Adverſary, to ſink the <hi>Point</hi> of his <hi>Sword,</hi> as you are Thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and wound you at the ſame time in the Belly? for it is certain your <hi>Sword</hi> cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend two parts at once, and if you <hi>quart</hi> your Head and Shoulders well, and Thruſt cloſs to your Adverſaries <hi>Sword</hi> above, then you are diſcovered below, which giveth him the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and Opportunity, if he can take it, to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> you, ſo this is as Uncertain and Unſecure as the other, and thus in moſt part of the other <hi>Leſſons,</hi> as well as in a plain Thruſt, doth a Man expoſe himſelf.</p>
                  <p>I can only except <hi>Flancanade</hi> and <hi>Batterie,</hi> but yet they are not ſo ſecure as <hi>Binding;</hi> for <hi>Bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> putteth your Adverſaries <hi>Sword</hi> quite out of the way, ſo that if you do it Strongly and Neatly, you may have your Thruſt home, and your Body in its <hi>Defenſive</hi> poſture again, before his <hi>Sword</hi> come into the ſtraight Line betwixt your Body and his, or be in ſuch a Diſpoſition as he can wound you with it, but no other <hi>Leſſon</hi> doth this ſo well as <hi>Binding,</hi> and therefore none of them is ſo Good or Safe.</p>
                  <p>Its true the moſt part of the other <hi>Leſſons</hi> do
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31657:20"/>by Cunning and Subtility, as it were Inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>Cheat</hi> and <hi>Dukoy</hi> your Adverſaries <hi>Sword</hi> out of the ſtraight Line, as all kind of <hi>Feints, &amp;c.</hi> And indeed I muſt confeſs he betrayes his <hi>Ignorance</hi> but too much, who ſuffers himſelf to be ſo <hi>Duckoyed</hi> and <hi>Cheated,</hi> both out of his Art, and I may ſay ſometimes his Life, with ſuch kind of Tricks; but <hi>Binding</hi> doth with ſo much <hi>Vigour</hi> and <hi>Firmneſs</hi> beat your Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>Sword,</hi> and force it out of the way, that unleſs he be a great <hi>Artiſt,</hi> it is impoſſible for him to Reſiſt, or Oppoſe it: and therefore it is the only ſecure play to be made uſe of for a Man's Life, and the only means to ſecure a Man, as ſaid is.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> becauſe of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries <hi>Sword</hi> being forced out of the way by it, which incapacitates him to Thruſt, until a Man hath given his thruſt, and recovered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his <hi>Defenſive Poſture</hi> again; but to make ſure Work, and to prevent more certainly a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> eſpecially if your Adverſary ſhould be a good <hi>Sword-man,</hi> you ſee I order your left Hand to make a kind of <hi>Parrade</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> at the giving in of every Thruſt, ſo that if this be done Neatly, and with Diſcretion, you are a great deal more ſecure from a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre-temps,</hi> than if you did omit it; And indeed I know no other way a Man can be certain of his Defence but this, and what I ſaid in my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31657:21"/>Reaſons to the preceeding Rule of the <hi>Contre-caveating Parrade,</hi> I may ſay here of <hi>Binding,</hi> that if it ſtand in need of the uſe of the left Hand, to ſecure it from a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> what Security can a Man expect, from playing any of the other <hi>Leſsons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this <hi>Binding</hi> with the uſe of the left Hand, doth not only ſave you as I ſaid from <hi>Contre-temps;</hi> But ſecondly, preſerves you alſo from thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſt,</hi> &amp; to make it with the uſe of the left Hand joyned to it, yet more effectual againſt <hi>Contre temps,</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſt;</hi> I have joyned a great and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable helper to it, by adviſing you not to reſt at all upon your Thruſt, but to recover your Body inſtantly to your <hi>Defenſive Poſture,</hi> after the giving in of every Thruſt, although your Thruſts ſhould not be deſigned home, but even half Thruſt; the cuſtom of reſting upon ones Thruſt is ſo Dangerous, and hath ſuch bad Conſequences, that I am perſwaded, he can never be a good <hi>Sword man,</hi> nor play ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely who is guilty of it, which I think is a ſufficient enough Reaſon, to make any Man of Judgement guard againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Now thir three, <hi>viz. Binding, The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the left Hand</hi> and <hi>the quick recovering of the Body after every Thruſt,</hi> are ſo Linked together, that they may become a certain Defence againſt <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſt,</hi> that any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31657:21"/>one of them without the other two, would not infallibly prove effectual, but the three being wrought and joyned together, do make ſo ſtrong a <hi>Barricade,</hi> and ſuch a ſecure and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nfallible Defence, that no <hi>Contre-temps</hi> in the World, nor any Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſts,</hi> can make a breach upon it, or render it Ineffectual.</p>
                  <p>And to make this the more clear, conſider that although by <hi>Binding</hi> you may force your Adverſaries <hi>Sword</hi> out of the way; yet if he be an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and have a quick Hand, he may before your Thruſt be home, bring his <hi>Sword</hi> into the right Line again, and give you a Thruſt as ſoon almoſt as you can give yours, although you was the firſt Mover: now the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to prevent this, is to ſtrengthen this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Binding,</hi> &amp; making it more ſecure by joyning the ſecond thing ordered to it, which was the help of the left Hand, notwithſtanding of which your Defence is yet uncertain, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, for although by uſing your left Hand, you may turn off the Thruſt he was giving home at you, yet if you reſt upon your thruſt, he may alter and change the giving in of his thruſt, and ſo cheat and deceive your left hand. Therefore to let your defence have all the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty imaginable you muſt yet farther ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it, and make it as it were impregnable, by joyning to the uſe of the left Hand, a quick Recovery of the Body, which Three
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31657:22"/>make the Defence upon your Purſute mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Certain and Infallible, if the Fault be not you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> own, or that you have not acquired <hi>Art</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to put them exactly in Practice.</p>
                  <p>And as for my Advice to <hi>Bind</hi> generally u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the outſide of the <hi>Sword,</hi> what I ſaid in my Reaſons to the preceeding Rule, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the making uſe of the <hi>Contre-caveating Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade</hi> generally upon the Outſide, may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaid here of <hi>Binding</hi> generally upon the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and therefore I refer you to what I ſaid there, not doubting but that I have fully convinced you, that (according to my Rule) there is no True and Secure Play with <hi>Sharps,</hi> and for a Mans Life, but by <hi>Binding,</hi> or <hi>Leſſons</hi> proceeding from it, the uſe of the left Hand, and a quick Recovery of the Body, perfecting with the <hi>Binding</hi> your Defence upon all your Purſutes: But if you deſign not your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Life, but only to diſable him, Then.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>V.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>Thruſt at his</hi> Sword-hand, Wreſt, <hi>or</hi> Arm, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> at his neareſt advanced</hi> Thigh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I find the more home a Man play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Thruſts, the more he expoſeth himſelf
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31657:22"/>and is lyable to Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſts,</hi> and albeit a Man in playing for Life and Death, is neceſſitat ſometimes to play home part of his Thruſts fully to the Body; yet when he doth not deſign the Life of his Adverſary, there is not that neceſſity for giving them ſo fully home, and ſo he needeth not ſo expoſe himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Now if he intends not to expoſe himſelf, and yet deſigns to diſable his Adverſary, What better Method can there be, then for him to Thruſt at thoſe parts of his Adverſaries Body which lie neareſt to him, and which he can reach without almoſt any kind of Hazard, or ſtretch! of his Body, ſuch as are the <hi>Arm, Wreſt, Sword-hand,</hi> and <hi>Thighs,</hi> and which if hit, do as ſoon diſable a Man, as any wounded Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Body, by reaſon of the many Veins, <hi>Arteries, Muſcles, Sinews,</hi> which are contained in them.</p>
                  <p>This is alſo an excellent Rule to be obſerved by Little, and Short Men, againſt thoſe who are Tall and Vigorous, and whoſe great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is alwayes to <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> when a Man playeth fully home any Thruſt to their Body, by reaſon of the Advantage they have of their long Reach or <hi>Elonge.</hi> It is alſo excellent to play much from the <hi>Reſpoſt</hi> upon ſuch kind of Perſons; But I think I need ſay no more for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31657:23"/>proving of this, the Rule it ſelf being ſo clear that it needeth no Commentary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VI.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>If your Adverſary be Haſty, Paſſionate, and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Furiouſly, and Irregularly, then with</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe it is found by Experience, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing encourages a Man more (who is of a Foreward Humour) to continue his violent Purſute, than the yeilding altogether to him, and not offering any wayes to reſiſt him; ſo that by Croſſing, Stopping, and Oppoſing his Fury, I mean that a Man ſhould alwayes ſo ſoon as ever he hath preſented his <hi>Sword,</hi> counterfeit a Real, or make a true half Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute, which are alone, and which half Purſute will be found extremely neceſſary in putting a ſtop to the Violence, and Fury of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
                  <p>For if you obſerve it, you will find for the moſt part, that all Foreward Humors if given Liberty to, do Extravague extremely, and become moſt Inſolent, Impertinent, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, but if they be in the leaſt check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it ſtopeth their Carrier, and maketh them truely diſcover their Natural Conſtitution,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31657:23"/>which is juſt upon the other Extreme of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Reproaches, and being Hectored and Baffled at all Hands.</p>
                  <p>But as in moſt part of things there is ſome Exceptions, ſo is there in this alſo, becauſe there may be ſome Men of a great deal of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Courage, who being ſenſible of their own <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>ignorance</hi> in the <hi>Art of the Sword,</hi> do find it abſolutely neceſſary (when it is their misfortune to be engaged) to ſupply that want by brisking it out, and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Adverſary if poſſible by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, although he be a very good <hi>Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> (but if he be ſuch, neither their Briskneſs nor Forwardneſs will do the buſineſs;) and as I ſaid, their Natural Force and Courage, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them wherewithall to puſh it to the very outmoſt, but there are few People of this ſlamp to be found, and where an Artiſt meets with one of thoſe, he will meet with twenty who are ſuch as I before deſcribed.</p>
                  <p>But engage with whom you pleaſe, either with <hi>Ignorants</hi> of the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond conſtitution</hi> and <hi>humour,</hi> or with <hi>Artiſts</hi> of either, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and vigorous <hi>half purſute,</hi> (for you can turn it into a true one when you pleaſe) is the only method to make your Art effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and their <hi>irregular paſſion</hi> and <hi>ignorant cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> to turn into ſmoak, and evaniſh in nothing.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:31657:24"/>
                  <p>I need but ſay little of the ſecond part of the Rule, which is, if your Adverſary ſhould be Careleſs, Laſh, Slow, or perhaps Timerous, that then with <hi>Calmneſs, Vigour,</hi> and <hi>Judgement,</hi> you ſhould purſue him, becauſe if he be Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, he can be no great <hi>Artiſt,</hi> at leaſt if he be, his Careleſneſs incapacitats him from putting his <hi>Art</hi> in practice, and conſequently reaping any benefit by it, and if he be <hi>Laſh,</hi> or <hi>Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> then although he have <hi>Art,</hi> yet it betoken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Cowardiceneſs,</hi> which alſo rendereth his <hi>Art</hi> uſeleſs to him, and in both thoſe Caſes you will have little to do, but to Divert your ſelf, and by uſing your <hi>Art</hi> with <hi>Judgement,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and Demonſtrate to him (by letting him feel ſome of your gentleſt Thruſts) how far you are Maſter of him, and how much he is in your Mercy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>With</hi> Calmneſs, Vigour, <hi>and</hi> Judgement, <hi>prevent your receiving one Thruſt for the giving ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, called (after that dangerous Name, and</hi> Artiſts Buge bear) <hi>a</hi> Contre-temps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe certainly all the <hi>Art</hi> in the World ſignifies not a <hi>Farthing,</hi> if a Man cannot by it infalliby Defend himſelf from a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> for what doth it avail or profit a Man, to purſue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31657:24"/>his Adverſary with all the <hi>Offenſive Art</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and wound him, if at the ſame time he is wounded himſelf, and that he doth not Back, or Second that his <hi>Offenſive Art,</hi> or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute, with his <hi>Defenſive Art,</hi> that ſo he may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hun a <hi>Contre-temps.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Can it be any ſatisfaction to him, that out of Eagerneſs to give his Adverſary a wound, he hath ſuffered himſelf by his Careleſneſs, to receive one perhaps much more Dangerous? Certainly to any <hi>Artiſt</hi> or Man of <hi>Judgement</hi> it can be none, but rather a matter of Regrate and Sorrow, that he ſhould have been at ſo much Pains and Trouble to acquire <hi>Art,</hi> and then to make ſo bad uſe of it, as the ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of exchanged Thruſts do too often prove; therefore to prevent ſuch Miſchiefs, obſerve this Rule, and what I have ſaid in my Reaſons for the Fourth, where you will find full Satisfaction, and infallible Directions both to prevent <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But me thinks I hear ſome Foreward <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> ſaying, that this Advice may be very good for <hi>Artiſts</hi> to obſerve, who have been Taught both how to Offend their Adverſary, and alſo to Defend themſelves, upon their Purſute from a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> if their Adverſary deſign one, but for ſuch <hi>Ignorants</hi> as they are,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31657:25"/>who would neither be at the Expences to im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ploy Maſters to Inſtruct them in this <hi>Art,</hi> nor if they did imploy them, could take the pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to follow it out, underſtand it, and put it in practice, it ſignifieth nothing, and all the tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that is ſpent in either Writting, or Adviſing it by word of Mouth, is but ſo much loſt time and Labour in vain.</p>
                  <p>In Anſwer to which, I ſhall in the firſt place grant, that as to what relates to them, it ſignifieth indeed nothing, in reſpect that they are Ignorant, and have not <hi>Art</hi> to make my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections effectual, for my Advices are an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of the beſt Rules in <hi>Fencing,</hi> which are to be moſt exactly obſerved, by the greateſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Sword-men,</hi> ſo that to all who are either <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi> or who have only the bare <hi>Theory,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Practice proportionable to it, thir forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Advices and Rules were never deſigned, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I before told in my Dedication.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, had I been to adviſe <hi>Ignorants,</hi> I would have deſired them to do the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, which is to be moſt Foreward, and to purſue moſt Furiouſly, and Irregularly, and ſo endeavour to wound their Adverſary, let it coſt themſelves what it would; and the Reaſon is clear, becauſe it is moſt evident, that all the Advantage an <hi>Ignorant</hi> can expect to have of an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> muſt flow from his Furious
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31657:25"/>and Violent Purſute, and endeavouring to force his Adverſary to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> with him every Thruſt, (but this will have but a ſmall Effect againſt a True <hi>Artiſt</hi>) for if he ſhould offer not to Purſue, but endeavour Naturally to Defend himſelf, a <hi>Sword man</hi> is in that Caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s much Maſter of him in his Play, as (to make a Compariſon) a Profeſſor of <hi>Divinity</hi> is Maſter of a young Student in his <hi>Theologie,</hi> or an Expert <hi>Mathematician</hi> Maſter of one who is but in his Inſtitutions of <hi>Geometry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore the only Method an <hi>Ignorant</hi> ſhould take to Baffle an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> is to be Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Irregular in his Motions, to ſee if by his Temerity and Rambling, he can Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and Force the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> becauſe he is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot and Smartly put to it, to be ſatisfied to give a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> that ſo he may make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as much as is in his power, in an equal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> who is almoſt certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o receive a Thruſt, as well as the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and perhaps more Dangerous, becauſe of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>'s knowing better to Plant and Adjuſt his Thruſts than he can do; for although an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi>'s Forewardneſs and Fury, may help him to force the giving of a <hi>Contre-temps</hi> by an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt;</hi> yet it can nowayes teach him to Adjuſt his Thruſt, or acquire any Advantage that way, which undeniably, and without any manner of Debate, all <hi>Artiſt</hi> have of <hi>Ignorants,</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:31657:26"/>by their knowing better how to <hi>Adjuſt</hi> and <hi>Plant</hi> their Thruſts, and will ſtill have ſo long as the other do really deſerve the Name of <hi>Ignorants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for all I have ſaid, I ſtill think to hear him inſiſt and maintain, that even to <hi>Artiſts</hi> this Advice of ſhuning <hi>Contre-temps</hi> will but ſignifie little, becauſe whoever will be but at the Trouble to viſit the <hi>Fencing-ſchools,</hi> ſhall ſcarcely ſee one Aſſault of ten, made either by <hi>Artiſts</hi> againſt <hi>Artiſts,</hi> or <hi>Artiſts</hi> againſt <hi>Ignorants,</hi> but what is ſo Compoſed and made up of <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> that one would think the greateſt Art they learn, and aime at, is to ſtrive who ſhall <hi>Contre-temps</hi> oftneſt, ſo that a Man is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitat to think one of two, either that the <hi>Art</hi> is of it ſelf unſufficient, to give that ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Contre-temps</hi> a Man would deſire, or that the Maſters play the Cheat, and teach not ſo much of the ſecurity of the <hi>Art</hi> as they know, ſo that if the Fault be in the Maſters, they ought not to be Encouraged, or Imployed and if it be in the <hi>Art,</hi> then it is not worth the Learnning, becauſe an <hi>Ignorant</hi> can <hi>Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temps</hi> an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> as well as the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> when it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſeth him, can <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> or Exchange Thruſts with the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> which maketh the <hi>Ignorant</hi>'s Forewardneſs as Advantagious, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and Uſeful to him, as all the <hi>Fallacious</hi> Tricks and Directions, which an <hi>Artiſt</hi> hath
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31657:26"/>been at the Pains and Expences to Underſtand and Learn from his Maſter, can be to him, and therefore that this Advice of mine to ſhun <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre-temps,</hi> is but a bare Speculation, and a thing Impracticable, and conſequently of as little uſe to an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> as to an <hi>Ignorant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One who is not an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> but ſuch an one as the Objecter (I mean an <hi>Ignorant</hi>) will be apt to think that what is here objected is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt unanſwerable, while in effect it is juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; And to give you ſome Satisfaction I ſhall take the pains to Anſwer it, which I hope to all underſtanding Men will prove a Motive to make them reſpect <hi>Fencing,</hi> and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, firſt to Underſtand and Practiſe, and when once that length, then to rely upon the Certainty and Infallibility of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Rules, which upon the contrary, if not exactly put in Practice according to my Directions, will prove both very Fallible and Uncertain, for what I ſpeak muſt be by them acted; other wayes all will prove falſe, and therefore if their expectation be not Anſwered, the Fault is their own, and none of mine.</p>
                  <p>But as to the Anſwer of the Objection, I ſay that it is neither the defect of the <hi>Art,</hi> which occaſioneth ſo many <hi>Contre-temps</hi> in the <hi>Fenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſchools,</hi> becauſe I dare be bold to ſay, that whoever practiſeth exactly the foregoing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31657:27"/>ſhall infalliby prevent and ſhun all <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> ſo that if thir Rules be ſufficient, and are a part of <hi>Fencing,</hi> then the <hi>Art</hi> is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſecure a Man from <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and therefore it is not any deficiency in the Art, which is the cauſe of ſo many <hi>Contre-temps</hi> in the <hi>Fencing-ſchools.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither is it the Maſters Ignorance, who know not to Teach this ſecure Play, becauſe to my certain knowledge, the moſt part of them, and thoſe who are beſt imployed, build their Art upon the ſame very Foundations &amp; Rules which I have given you (although I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs they are Guilty of ſome Abuſes and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions in their Schools, which I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have Rectified, for which ſee my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Obſervation) ſo that it cannot be their <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> in not knowing to Teach this ſecure kind of Play, which is the cauſe of ſo many <hi>Contre-temps.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor is it likewiſe the Maſters playing the Cheat, in not Teaching; or keeping ſecret, and not Revealing and Diſcovering to their Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, when they give them their Leſſons, the Hazard and Danger of <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> which are exchanged in Schools; No, the Fault lieth not in any of theſe, but in the Scholar, who although his Maſter ſhew him the way how to prevent <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and the Danger that is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31657:27"/>in them; yet will not be at the pains to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Directions, but will follow his own Method, becauſe he thinketh himſelf, if he hath been but three Months at the School, as Dexterous and Underſtanding as his Maſter, and that he ſtandeth in need no more of his Advice, but may be his own Governour and Director.</p>
                  <p>This is the true Reaſon why we ſee ſo many <hi>Contre-temps</hi> in Schools, and conſequently have ſo many bad <hi>Sword-men</hi> in the Kingdom, but to a true <hi>Artiſt</hi> who hath exactly followed his Maſters Advice, and hath acquired ſufficient Practice; I maintain that the foregoing Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, will be moſt Seaſonable, Acceptable, &amp; Uſeful, let <hi>Ignorants</hi> talk what they will.</p>
                  <p>And as for their being certain to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> with an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> when they pleaſe to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in that Hazard, I poſitively deny it, for upon the contrary I mantain that a true <hi>Artiſt</hi> may, (provided he practiſe exactly the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Rules) infallibly ſave and keep himſelf from being <hi>Contre-temped,</hi> let the <hi>Ignorant</hi> Force and Puſh as he pleaſeth, and if the <hi>Artiſt</hi> do it not, it is not the Fault, or any Defect or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency in the Art it ſelf, but only his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and failing to make uſe of the Security that his Art is able to furniſh him with; and as upon the one Hand an <hi>Artiſt</hi> can infallibly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31657:28"/>ſave himſelf from a <hi>Contretemps</hi> by an <hi>Ignorant,</hi> I deny not but one <hi>Artiſt</hi> may <hi>Contre-temps</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (becauſe it is for them chiefly that this Direction or Rule for ſhunning of <hi>Contretemps</hi> was deſigned) ſo upon the other, he can infalli-<hi>Contre-temps</hi> with the <hi>Ignorant</hi> as often as he pleaſeth, and it ſhall not be in the <hi>Ignorants</hi> power to hinder or prevent him.</p>
                  <p>For you muſt underſtand that to give a true and real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> doth really require <hi>Judgement</hi> and a ſwift and juſt Hand, as I ſhall immediately ſhew you, and here I deſire you to make a Diſtinction, betwixt an <hi>Ignorants Contre-temping</hi> an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and his Forcing the <hi>Artiſt</hi> by the Violence and Fury of his Purſute, for his own Eaſe and Satisfaction to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> him, for this <hi>Laſt</hi> I do not deny, but voluntarly acknowledges, that an <hi>Artiſt</hi> may be ſo preſſed, that when he findeth he can do no better, he is ſatisfied, (rather than to let the <hi>Ignorant</hi> have any Advantage of him) to put himſelf in the ſame Hazard with him, by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> him, and when People ſometimes ſee an <hi>Artiſt</hi> Reduced to this ſtrait, they are ſo far miſtaken, as to think that the <hi>Ignorant contre-temps</hi> him, whereas it is really the <hi>Artiſt</hi> that <hi>contre-tempeth</hi> the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> that he may be ſaid to have loſt no Advantage by his Art, nor the <hi>Ignorant</hi> to have gotten any by his <hi>Ignorance</hi> and Furious <hi>Forewardneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:31657:28"/>
                  <p>But as upon the one Hand, I acknowledge that an <hi>Artiſt</hi> may be ſo preſſed with an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> that he is neceſſitate to Venture and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard a <hi>Contre-temps</hi> with him, ſo upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I poſitively deny, that it is in the power of any <hi>Ignorant</hi> to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> a Perſon who is really an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and my Reaſon is, becauſe as I ſaid before, to give a real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> doth really require <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>a ſwift and juſt Hand;</hi> and that no <hi>Ignorant</hi> can be ſuppoſed to have, and that it requireth thoſe Three to make it evident thus.</p>
                  <p>If an <hi>Ignroant</hi> give a real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> it muſt be given juſt as the <hi>Artiſt</hi> is Thruſting at him, and neither before nor after, for if it be either before or after, then it is no <hi>Contre temps;</hi> now ſuppoſe it be before the <hi>Artiſt</hi> Thruſt, then the <hi>Artiſt</hi> will not give one Thruſt for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and therefore it is no <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> but the Fault of the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> who did not Defend the Purſute of the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and ſo it is a fair Thruſt, and cannot be called a <hi>Contre temps;</hi> and if it be after the <hi>Artiſt</hi> hath Thruſt, that the <hi>Ignorant</hi> giveth him a Thruſt; then nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be called a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> but rather a Thruſt from the <hi>Reſpoſt;</hi> and ſo it was the <hi>Artiſts</hi> Fault in not Defending himſelf better upon his own Purſute, and not the <hi>Ignorants</hi> Judgement that made him give it.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:31657:29"/>
                  <p>Now as it cannot be called a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> which is either given before, or after an <hi>Artiſt</hi> doth Thruſt, ſo that only can be called a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre-temps,</hi> which is given at the ſame very nick of time the <hi>Artiſt</hi> is Truſting, for then both will undoubtedly receive a Thruſt at the ſame time; (unleſs one of them prevent it by the help of the left Hand) and this is that which can only be called a real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and that an <hi>Ignorant</hi> can give this, I deny for three Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; The firſt is, that he muſt have the Judgement to Time his Thruſt, juſt as the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> is Thruſting; and the ſecond, and third, that he muſt both have a quick Hand to be as ſoon home as the <hi>Artiſt;</hi> and a juſt Hand to Plant his Thruſt right, none of which an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> can be ſaid to have; for not having the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> he cannot have the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, and without Practice (which none will ſay he can pretend to) he can neither have a Juſt, nor Swift Hand: And therefore that it is not in the power of an <hi>Ignorant,</hi> to give an <hi>Artiſt</hi> a real <hi>Contre temps</hi> will hold good, as I think I have ſufficiently made appear. And alſo that to give a real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> is required <hi>Judgement,</hi> and <hi>a Swift and Juſt Hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And upon the contrary, that an <hi>Artiſt</hi> can infallibly <hi>Contre-temps</hi> with an <hi>Ignorant,</hi> as often as he pleaſeth, and it ſhall not be in the <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:31657:29"/>power to prevent it, is very clear, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Judgement, a quick Haud,</hi> and <hi>the practice to Adjuſt a Thruſt,</hi> being the Three things which render an <hi>Ignorant</hi> incapable to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> it will follow, that an <hi>Artiſt</hi> having theſe three Advantages, they give to him that, which the want of them diveſt the <hi>Ignorant</hi> of; ſo that the <hi>Ignorant</hi> being rendered uncapable to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> by the want of them, by the Rule of Contraries, the <hi>Artiſt</hi> by having them, is made capable to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> when and how often he pleaſeth.</p>
                  <p>So by this time, I doubt not but you are ſenſible of the weakneſs of the Objection, and how unreaſonable and frivolous it is, and alſo underſtand what Advantages a Man's Art giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him upon the one Hand, and what Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies and Hazards his <hi>Ignorance</hi> upon the other doth expoſe him to; and if ſo, then I need not inquire which of the two you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be, whether a <hi>Judicious Artiſt,</hi> or a <hi>Furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Foreward Ignorant;</hi> ſeing your very Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the one, would accuſe you of Folly; and your Deſpiſing the other, diſcover your Sloth and Careleſneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="rule">
                  <head>RULE <hi>VIII.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Now to put a cloſe to my Rules, let them be all done within Diſtance as much as poſſible,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:31657:30"/>
                  <p>The Reaſons upon which this Rule is Grounded, are.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe the cloſer a Man play to his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary (if he be Maſter of the <hi>Defenſive part</hi>) he playeth ſo much the ſecurer for himſelf, and is in a better Capacity to Hurt or Offend his Adverſary, then when he is without Diſtance, and is neceſſitate before the giving in of every Thruſt to approach, for this both diſordereth his own Body, by expoſing it more to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre-temps</hi> of his Adverſary, and alſo maketh his Purſute not ſo effectual, in reſpect that it is not ſo quick and ſmart, as when it is done within Diſtance; For playing within Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, all your Thruſts may be given in the twinckling of an Eye, and a great deal more certain as to the <hi>Planting,</hi> being only done with the <hi>Spring</hi> of your <hi>Arm,</hi> and without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any <hi>Elonge</hi> of the Body, which are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third things adviſed in this laſt Rule</p>
                  <p>Now it is moſt certain, that all Thruſts given only with a <hi>Spring</hi> or <hi>Jerk</hi> of the <hi>Arm,</hi> are a great deal more Strong, Quick, and Firme, then when they are performed with an <hi>Elonge,</hi> becauſe the Elonging or Stretching the reſt of your Body, weakneth and taketh away both the Force of the <hi>Spring,</hi> and Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Thruſt:</hi> Therefore to Play only with a <hi>Spring</hi> of the <hi>Arm,</hi> and with as little a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31657:30"/>
                     <hi>Stretch</hi> or <hi>Elonge</hi> as poſſible, is the only beſt way to play both ſmartly, and ſecurely: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if a Man accuſtome himſelf to great Stretches, he runneth into two Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the one is the expoſing his Body by it to the <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt</hi> of his Adverſary, which if he did not ſtretch, would not be ſo much expoſed; The other is the Danger he putteth himſelf in, if his Feet ſhould ſlip, and he fall, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo prevented if he play within Diſtance, only with a <hi>Spring of the Arm,</hi> and with little or no <hi>Stretch:</hi> And therefore if it were but only upon this one Account, I think a Man ſhould ſhun <hi>Stretching</hi> as much as poſſible. A Man hath likewiſe this Advantage by playing cloſs to his Adverſary, that it preventeth the Variety of Leſſons which would make him the more uncertain of the <hi>Parrade.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that you may the better do it, I gave you an Advice in my ſecond Rule, which will be of great uſe to prevent your <hi>Stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and it was, <hi>That you ſhould ſtill keep your Heels as near other as poſſible,</hi> which I omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpeak to in that place, thinking it to come more a <hi>Propos</hi> here; now if you but conſider it, you will find that this keeping of your Heels near other, when you are even without Diſtance, but more eſpecially when you are within, doth make your Thruſt come
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31657:31"/>the farther home, and reach your Adverſary with a far leſs <hi>Stretch</hi> of the Body, then if your Heels were keep a good way aſunder, ſo that playing within Diſtance, as I order you, if your Heels be cloſs, the ſtepping foreward a Foot, with your advanced Foot, will bring your Thruſt as far home, as your full <hi>Stretch</hi> would have done, if your hindmoſt Heel had been far diſtant from your advanced; ſo that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your hindermoſt Heel, cloſs almoſt to your advanced Heel and being within Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, you will almoſt without any <hi>Stretch</hi> of the Body, only by ſtepping foreward a little with your advanced Foot, and uſing the <hi>Spring</hi> of your Arm, ſheath your <hi>Sword</hi> to the very middle in your Adverſarie's Body, if he do not oppoſe you.</p>
                  <p>But this is not all the Advantage you reap by keeping your Heels near; for it not only carrieth home your Thruſt father; but alſo is a great means to help you to recover your Body quickly after every Thruſt, which was one of the Particulars I adviſed in the fourth Rule. Now it is clear, that ſo long as a Man playeth at his full <hi>Stretch,</hi> he can never ſo quickly recover his Body, as he can do when he is at a half <hi>Stretch,</hi> nor ſo ſoon at a half <hi>Stretch,</hi> as he can do when he maketh little or no <hi>Stretch;</hi> and ſeing the keeping of his hinder Heel near to his advanced, preventeth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31657:31"/>his <hi>Stretching,</hi> and the leſs that he <hi>Stretcheth,</hi> the quicklier he will recover his Body, then it doth certainly follow, that the keeping his Heels near other, is a great means to facilitate the quick recovery of his Body after every Thruſt, which was that I deſigned to prove.</p>
                  <p>So there remains only, that I ſhould ſpeak to the third thing propoſed in my firſt Rule, which I delayed till now, deſigning to cloſe the Reaſons for my Rules with a ſhort Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon it, which is alſo the laſt Advice in this my laſt Rule, to wit, <hi>That</hi> Judgement <hi>accompany all your Actions, both in their Beginning, Procedure, and Cloſe;</hi> and indeed without it all I have ſaid would ſignifie but little, for to make a ſhort Detail, What would it ſignifie to you? your having <hi>Calmneſs,</hi> and <hi>Vigour,</hi> if you had not <hi>Judgement</hi> to direct you, how to make uſe of the Advantage you have by them; And what would the keeping of a Cloſs and Thinn Guard ſignifie to you, if you had not your <hi>Judgement</hi> in defending yourſelf upon it, or purſuing your Adverſary from it; What would it ſignifie alſo to you, that you have Directions to prevent <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> if you have not <hi>Judgement</hi> to know when to Practiſe them, and in ſhort what doth the whole <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Sword</hi> ſignifie without <hi>Judgement,</hi> certainly for very little or no uſe at all.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:31657:32"/>
                  <p>Now as upon the one Hand an <hi>Artiſt</hi> is liable to a great many Inconveniencies by the want of it, ſo upon the other his having it, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him in a Capacity, and ſets him at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, notwithſtanding my Directions I have given him, (although I confeſs they are the ſecureſt I can think upon, or imagine) to chooſe what <hi>Parrades,</hi> and what <hi>Leſſons</hi> he ſhall think moſt fitt and agreeable to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Play, and Humour of his Adverſary, although thoſe <hi>Leſſons</hi> which he might pitch upon in reſpect of ſome Mens play, would be found to be moſt looſe and uncertain; but in reſpect of the Perſon he is to play them upon, Judicious and Good, becauſe by his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hath found that ſuch <hi>Leſſons</hi> will have as good effect againſt ſuch a Perſon, as the moſt ſecure againſt one of another Humour, for if it were other wayes, and had not his Liberty of chooſe, he would then be tyed up, and confined to my Directions; or I may ſay, to my particular Judgement, which is the rendering his own uſeleſs, and is juſt contrary to what I ſo much recommended; but there muſt be great care taken, that a Man abuſe not this Liberty, and Allowance which is given him, and that he be certain his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be not falſe, but Grounded upon Art and Reaſon before he Adventure, and take upon him to make any conſiderable Change or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31657:32"/>in Directions, which in the ſtrickeſt Senſe muſt be confeſſed to be the moſt ſecure, againſt all Play and Humours whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>But that I may end this with a Compariſon, <hi>Fencing</hi> without <hi>Judgement,</hi> is juſt like a Watch without a <hi>Spring,</hi> a Neat peice of Work with a great many fine Wheels, but without any Motion, the want of which maketh her uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: And ſo is the Art of <hi>Fencing</hi> a curious Art, wherein there are a great many fine <hi>Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and excellent <hi>Rules,</hi> but for lack of <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (which is its <hi>Spring</hi>) all lieth Dead, and is Uſeleſs; but once apply the <hi>Spring,</hi> and ſet it in Motion and a going, and then it becometh a moſt Quick and Lively Exerciſe, and (as a <hi>Watch</hi>) an Ornament fit for all Gentlemen to carry about with them, and as a compleat <hi>Watch</hi> with a <hi>Spring</hi> ſheweth a Man the Hour of the Day, that ſo he may know how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his time and actions; ſo doth <hi>Fencing</hi> directed by <hi>Judgement,</hi> diſcover to a Man the Hazards and Inconveniencies he is expoſed to, and the means to ſhun and prevent them, by his diſpoſing of the ſeveral Branches of his <hi>Art</hi> ſo and ſo, as ſhe ſhall direct him.</p>
                  <p>And farther, as the <hi>Spring</hi> of a <hi>Watch</hi> doth cauſe its Hand to point to that Hour, which is moſt needful to be known; ſo doth <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> direct a Man's Hand, to point with his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31657:33"/>
                     <hi>Sword,</hi> and Thruſt at ſuch parts of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarres Body, which do moſt expoſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves to him, and which are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt fit to be Attacqued; ſo that without her, there can be no true <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and where ſhe preſides, all will go well, and as one would wiſh that is, make the preceeding Rules anſwer my Deſign, which was, infallibly to direct a Man, to defend himſelf againſt the Attacques of all Perſons with <hi>Sharpes,</hi> which I doubt not but I have ſufficiently done, if they be exactly obſerved; and I am confident, if they fail, it can be imputed to no defect in the Directions, but to the weakneſs and want of Art in the Perſon, who is to put them in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and therefore the blame muſt lye at their Door, and not at mine; for it is Acting, and not Talking, that in this Caſe muſt do the Buſineſs.</p>
                  <p>Having now finiſhed my Rules, with the Reaſons upon which they are Grounded, I ſhall in the laſt place proceed to the third thing I at firſt propoſed, which was, to give you ſome Obſervations, which will be neither Unneceſſary, nor Unpleaſant.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:31657:33"/>
               <head>Thirdly, Some REMARKES and OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERVATIONS, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>IN the Firſt place I obſerve, let <hi>Ignorants</hi> talk what they pleaſe, and undervalue both <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Artiſts</hi> as much as is in their power; yet ſtill it is an undeniable Truth, that <hi>Artiſts</hi> have three conſiderable Advantages of them, which is, firſt, <hi>The knowing to Parrie, and actually Parreing a plain Thruſt, better than they can do;</hi> For I ſhall Engage for what any Man pleaſeth, That, ſet up an <hi>Ignorant</hi> to me at the Wall, who was never taught any thing of the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Sword;</hi> I ſhall with the <hi>Art</hi> I have, give him half a Dozen <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> diſtinctly one after another, and it ſhall not be in his power to <hi>Parrie,</hi> or Defend himſelf from one <hi>ſingle Thruſt</hi> of all the ſix, and upon the other Hand, let him Thruſt at me twenty <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> at the Wall, he ſhall not Touch me with one of them; And if this be true (which may be eaſily put to a Trial, whether it be ſo or not) then certainly the <hi>Artiſt</hi> as I ſaid, hath this firſt Advantage of an <hi>Ignorant,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:31657:34"/>that he can <hi>Parrie</hi> and Defend himſelf better then the <hi>Ignorant</hi> can do for his Heart.</p>
               <p>But perhaps when ſome Perſons are read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, who have ſeen me when I have been in the <hi>Fencing-ſchools,</hi> receive either <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> at the Wall, from thoſe who were Thruſting upon me, or in Aſſault when I was playing as the would judge my beſt, they will be apt to challenge me, and ask how I come to Aſſert things, the contrary of which they have ſeen with their own Eyes; As firſt, <hi>That I have been ſo far from Parreing twenty</hi> plain Thruſts <hi>upon end, that they have ſeen me hitt once in three or four;</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>That in Aſsaulting, notwithſtanding the many exact Rules I pretend to give, to ſave a Man from</hi> Contre-temps; yet they have ſeen me ſeveral times <hi>Contre-temped,</hi> and it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that if I could not Defend my ſelf with my own Rules from <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> another will hardly do it: Therefore my Rules will not prove ſo very infallible as I imagine them to be, and that I ſhould not have been ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive in the Commendation of them, ſeing that I my ſelf know them to have failed me, in that which I do moſt commend them for, <hi>viz. Their ſecurity againſt</hi> Contre-temps.</p>
               <p>I know thir will be the Thoughts and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections of ſome, who will peruſe thir Sheet more out of a Curioſity to get ſomething to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31657:34"/>Object againſt me, then a deſire to reap any Profit or Advantage by them, and therefore I thought fit to ſet them down in this place, that ſo I might Anſwer them.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, I do not believe that any Man will ſay, he ever ſaw me receive a <hi>plain Thruſt</hi> at the Wall from any <hi>Ignorant,</hi> which is what I affirmed, I would Defend my ſelf from; for if I were not able with the <hi>Art</hi> I have certainly to Defend my ſelf at the Wall, from the <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> of all <hi>Ignorants,</hi> I ſhould then throw down my <hi>Fleuret,</hi> and underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue <hi>Fencing</hi> ſo much, that I ſhould never more enquire after it, or any wayes, encourage the Profeſſors of it, but ſhould do all that lay in my power to diſcover its inſufficiency, that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men might not be for the Future Impoſed u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon and Cheated, both out of their Money &amp; Time by it. But although I deny my being hitt at the Wall by the <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> of <hi>Ignorants;</hi> yet I confeſs I have been often hitt by <hi>Artiſts,</hi> and I do not almoſt remember that ever I was bitt with <hi>plain Thruſts,</hi> ſince I underſtood any thing of this <hi>Art,</hi> but what was given me either by thoſe who were actually Scholars at the Time, and therefore were no <hi>Ignorants;</hi> or thoſe who had been once Scholars, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo no wayes deſerved the Name of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants,</hi> and for my being hitt with a <hi>plain
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31657:35"/>Thruſt</hi> by ſuch, I do no deny it, neither doth it any wayes reflect upon me, becauſe for one <hi>Sword-man</hi> to be hitt with a <hi>plain Thruſt</hi> by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is no Diſparagement at all, but a very conſiderable one it is, if an <hi>Artiſt</hi> cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly Defend himſelf againſt the <hi>plain Thruſts</hi> of any <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and that I am not able to do that, I poſitively deny, and refers the Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to a Trial, when ever it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by Perſons who are worth the giving Satisfaction to in ſuch a Matter; therefore when ſuch Perſons accuſe me of being hitt with <hi>plain Thruſts,</hi> they would do well to be ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous as to confeſs, that thoſe Thruſts were really given me by <hi>Artiſts,</hi> which I ſhall willingly confeſs, and not by <hi>Ignorants,</hi> which I poſitively deny, for if that were, they would indeed have good Reaſon to laugh both at me, and my Directions.</p>
               <p>But as to the ſecond, which is, <hi>My receiving</hi> Contre temps <hi>in Aſſaults, notwithſtanding of what I could do to prevent them,</hi> which not only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the inſufficiency of my Rules to prevent <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> but alſo my diſingenuity in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, and Accounting Rules to be Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, which I by my own proper Experience have found oftner then once, to be both Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and Uncertain.</p>
               <p>This Objection I confeſs cometh ſomewhat
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31657:35"/>cloſer to me than the former did, and I believe I have ſtarted it ſo fairely, that none who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders either this or the former, but will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, I have ſaid as much both againſt my ſelf, and to make this <hi>Art</hi> of no Repute, as any <hi>Ignorant</hi> whatſoever could do, and I the rather like to make all the Objections poſſible againſt it, that People may be convinced I deal above Board, and that there lyeth no Cheat in the Matter; and that alſo by Anſwering all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, I may in a manner (by reaſoning ſo fairely with them) force them to confeſs and acknowledge, that the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Sword</hi> is not only a Pleaſant, but alſo an Uſeful and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Art,</hi> worthy of the Study of all, but more eſpecially of the <hi>Gentry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in Anſwer to the Objection, although <hi>I</hi> confeſs I have received many <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and notwithſtanding of all the <hi>Art</hi> I have, do ſtill Fear them when <hi>I</hi> am Aſſaulting, and although <hi>I</hi> might alſo alledge what <hi>I</hi> did in the Anſwer, to the preceeding Objection, that all the <hi>Contre-temps</hi> ever I received were from <hi>Artiſts,</hi> (for <hi>I</hi> poſitively deny that any <hi>Ignorant</hi> can give an <hi>Artiſt</hi> a reall <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made appear in my Reaſons for the Seventh Rule, to which I refer you) and the moſt part of the <hi>Thruſts,</hi> that were Exchanged one for another, were alſo for the moſt Part from <hi>Artiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:31657:36"/>and not from <hi>Ignorants,</hi> and conſequently no diſparagement to me; yet paſſing by that, and granting theſe exchanged Thruſts were given by <hi>Ignorants,</hi> I ſhall give you two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the one ſhewing why any <hi>Artiſt,</hi> be he never ſo Expert, may come to receive one Thruſt for another from an <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and the other ſhewing that he may receive either a real <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> or one Thruſt for another from an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> and yet that it can be no reflection upon my Rules, which, as I ſaid, will prove ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible if exactly obſerved.</p>
               <p>And the Reaſon of the firſt (which is, any <hi>Artiſts</hi> receiving one Thruſt for another from an <hi>Ignorant</hi>) is that when People Aſſault, it is commonly with <hi>Blunts,</hi> and when an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> who undervalueth the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and truſteth all to his own Forewardneſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſired by an <hi>Artiſt</hi> to ſhew his Natural Play, he very well conſidering that he can receive no prejudice by his being hitt with a blu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>Fleuret,</hi> Ruſheth and Rambleth ſtill forewards (let him receive never ſo many Thruſts) until he either hitteth the <hi>Artiſt</hi> with one of his Rambling Thruſts, or other wayes cometh ſo cloſs, that the <hi>Artiſt</hi> muſt incloſe with him, and he thinketh, if he hath given the <hi>Artiſt</hi> but one Thruſt (although he himſelf ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive three or four in the time they are play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) that he hath carried the Day, and quite
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31657:36"/>run down the Art of <hi>Fencing,</hi> whereas if they were either to play with Real <hi>Sharps,</hi> or with <hi>Fleurets</hi> having a quarter of an Inch of a point beyond the button, I make not the leaſt doubt, but their rambling would be a little ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and they would take better notice to what they did, it being Natural even for the moſt Foreward and Boldeſt of Men, to endeavour to ſave themſelves by putting a little ſtop to their Purſute, when they perceive a Sharp point oppoſite to, and ready to wound, them, and without which ſtop or pauſe, they are ſenſible they might run the Risk, if not of loſing their Life; yet at leaſt of being hurt, and ſo ſmarting for their raſh Fotewardneſs: ſo this is the Reaſon why <hi>Artiſts</hi> may receive one Thruſt for another from <hi>Ignorants,</hi> to wit, <hi>Their Aſſaulting commonly with</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unts; Therefore to prevent this inconveniency, if I were to play with an <hi>Ignorant</hi> for a Wager, I would play alwayes with pointed <hi>Fleurets,</hi> and then in GOD's Name let him Ramble his Belly full; For in that caſe I would know a way to come at him, which might perhaps cauſe him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent his Forewardneſs.</p>
               <p>But the Reaſon of the ſecond, (which is that an <hi>Artiſt</hi> may either receive a Real <hi>Centre temps</hi> or one Thruſt for another, (commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Exchanged Thruſts</hi>) from another <hi>Artiſt</hi>) is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31657:37"/>that although they play never ſo warrily, yet if they fail in the leaſt, to make uſe of the exact contraries to <hi>Contre-temps</hi> and Thruſts from the <hi>Reſpoſt,</hi> which I have given them, they expoſe themſelves to both, and I muſt confeſs, the Directions are ſo Nice and Difficult to be performed, that there are even but few <hi>Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who are able to put them exactly in practice; ſo that it is not the defect of the Rules, but the Fault of the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> in not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them ſtrictly in practice, that is, the cauſe of his being either <hi>Hitt, Contre-temped,</hi> or <hi>Reſpoſted:</hi> This Reaſon I alſo give for my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any of the Three in Aſſault from <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> or the firſt and laſt from <hi>Ignorants;</hi> and I much doubt, if it be poſſible for ordinary <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> to obſerve them altogether exactly, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the nearer they come to the exact Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of them, they are certainly ſo much the ſecurer; And if it be asked why I give Rules ſo difficult, that neither, I my ſelf, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sword-men</hi> when they are even at their greateſt perfection can without a great deal of difficulty exactly obſerve? It is Anſwered, That in this, I Reſemble the <hi>Divines,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they give moſt excellent Rules for Holy Living and Dying, which cannot but be confeſſed by all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to be moſt <hi>Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>Orthodox;</hi> yet find great Difficulty themſelves to Live up to that pitch of <hi>Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:31657:37"/>and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which they require exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of others under the pain of <hi>Eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and yet none will be ſo bold as to ſay, becauſe thoſe Rules are not but with great Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty exactly obſerved, that therefore they are not ſufficient, and infallibly certain, to bring Salvation to all who exactly obſerve, and ſquare their Lives and Actions conform to them: The Parallel I confeſs betwixt thirtwo Subjects is altogether unequal; yet the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon will hold good, that although an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> may receive a Thruſt, or be <hi>Contre-temped</hi> or <hi>Reſpoſted,</hi> becauſe of his failing to obſerve exactly my Directions; yet that the Directions may be, and are in themſelves abſolutely ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and infallible, for the preſervation of one who exactly obſerves them, from all kind of Thruſts whatſoever, I doubt not but what I have ſaid, will be thought to be, by all rational Men, a ſufficient Anſwer, both to the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and for proving the ſufficiency of my Rules, therefore I ſhall proceed where I left; And ſhew, that.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Advantage <hi>Artiſts</hi> have over <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants,</hi> is, in <hi>Planting</hi> or <hi>Adjuſting</hi> a Thruſt, which no Man will controvert, ſeing it is not to be imagined, that an <hi>Ignorant</hi> who perhaps did never thruſt ſix Thruſts in his Life-time, can be ſo certain to hitt the part of the Body he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31657:38"/>aimeth at, as an <hi>Artiſt</hi> will be, who hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taught how to <hi>Plant,</hi> and is now and then pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing himſelf with it.</p>
               <p>And the Third is the having of <hi>Judgement,</hi> for I ſuppoſe all <hi>Artiſts</hi> to have that, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes they are really no <hi>Artiſts</hi> but <hi>Ignorants</hi> in Maſquerad, that is to ſay, they pretend to <hi>Art,</hi> becauſe they have been ſome time at the <hi>Fencing ſchool,</hi> and ſo under that Cloak of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once a Scholar, they conceal their <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> but if they be real <hi>Artiſts</hi> they muſt have the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> and that no <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> can have, becauſe it is unſeparably joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Art it ſelf, and is only acquired by practiſing of it, and that no <hi>Ignorant</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, who never was at the Pains and Trouble, ſo much as to enquire after it, let alone to be at the Toile to gain it by practice, which is the only true way to come at it.</p>
               <p>Now the Advantage an <hi>Artiſt</hi> hath over a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ignorant,</hi> by having this <hi>Judgement,</hi> is that by it he can know when ſuch and ſuch a Part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Adverſaries Body is open to him, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Leſso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> are moſt proper to offend ſuch parts as are expoſed, and even although his Adverſary ſhould not be Open but upon a Cloſs Guard, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſurn ſheth him with means to make him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover himſelf and give an Open: As alſo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Teatheth him in ſome meaſure to underſtand
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:31657:38"/>and know, when, and at what part of his own Body, his Adverſary deſignes to Attacque him: all this and a great deal more it doth to an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> but an <hi>Ignorant</hi> not having it, he is fruſtrate of all theſe preceeding Advantages, and therefore certainly at a great deal of loſs for the want of it, ſo that it cannot be denied, but this of having <hi>Judgement</hi> is the Third con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Advantage, that all true <hi>Artiſts</hi> have over <hi>Ignorants.</hi> I could give you ſeveral other Inſtances in which <hi>Artiſts</hi> have conſiderable Advantages, but I think what I have ſaid ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient as to this Particular.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I obſerve that in the <hi>Fencing ſchools</hi> (and that not only of this Kingdom, but <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>France</hi> alſo) there are ſeveral Abuſes, and things committed which I would have rectified, both for the Benefit of the Scholars, and Reputation of the Maſters; although I know it will be thought ſomewhat ſtrange, that after having ſaid ſo much in Commendation of <hi>Fencing</hi> it ſelf, I ſhould at laſt reflect upon its Profeſſors and Teachers.</p>
               <p>But to that I Anſwer, That although the Art be Grounded upon undeniable Truths and infallible Reaſons; yet that is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but many who profeſs it may be ſubject to Errours, for I am far from attributing Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility to them: And I confeſs I am ſorry, I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:31657:39"/>ſhould be neceſſitate to differ from many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, in circumſtances ſo conſiderably tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the accompliſhment and perfecting of <hi>Sword men,</hi> but my Opinion being backed with ſo many, and ſtrong Reaſons (the Truth and Weight whereof I earneſtly recommend to the ſerious Reflection of the Reader,) I cannot but maintain and defend it; until by as ſtrong and convincing Reaſons as I have given for it, I am perſwaded of the contrary.</p>
               <p>Seing therefore my Propoſals are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Reaſon, and not upon other Mens practices, I expect they will convince me by it, for that practice which is againſt Reaſon, is but deceitful and falſe, and as it is to the Eternal Fame of the great DUKE of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> that he was the firſt who Rectified the Abuſes of Riding in the <hi>Academies,</hi> by finding out a new and infallible Method for dreſſing Horſes, which was not thought of before, and which at firſt had no doubt many Oppoſers, until from the reaſonableneſs and great Succeſs it had, they were neceſſitate to acknowledge its Excellency and Certainty: So I hope I ſhall have the Honour to be one of the firſt who hath publickly propoſed the Rectifying of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes commonly committed in <hi>Fencing ſchools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt whereof is, <hi>The giving Scholars at their very firſt Entering to the School, heavy</hi> Fleurets
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31657:39"/>
                  <hi>to take their Leſſons with;</hi> And the Reaſon they give is, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the uſing a weighty</hi> Fleuret <hi>ſtrengthneth their</hi> Arms <hi>and</hi> Wreſts, <hi>and maketh them when they come afterwards to Aſſault with light</hi> Fleurets, <hi>to handle them a great deal more Eaſily and Nimbly, then they would have done, had they been ſtill, accuſtomed to play with light ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this I grant, for it cannot be denied, but that which I condemn, is, their giving theſe heavy <hi>Fleurets</hi> to Schollars at their very firſt entring to them, when they underſtand not ſo much as how to give in a <hi>Plain Thruſt,</hi> or to move their <hi>Fleuret</hi> regularly any way, for it is certain that they never being accuſtomed to move their <hi>Wreſts,</hi> the firſt time that they uſe that Motion it will be a trouble to them, and make their <hi>Sinewes</hi> Ake, although they had nothing in their Hands at all, let alone a ſtiff heavy <hi>Fleuret,</hi> juſt as a Man when he is firſt Learning to <hi>Elonge</hi> or ſtretch, the <hi>Sinewes</hi> of his <hi>Thighs</hi> will Ake for a Day or two after, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he force not himſelf to a full <hi>ſtretch:</hi> And as it would be thought a little ſtrange for a Maſter to force a young Schollar the very firſt or Second Day after his firſt entring to the School to his full <hi>Stretch,</hi> or before he hath by cuſtome made <hi>Elonging</hi> familiar and eaſy to him; ſo I ſay, at the beginning a Schollar ſhould make uſe of a very light <hi>Fleuret</hi> untill
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:31657:40"/>by a little Practice and Uſe, his <hi>Wreſt</hi> be acquainted with the turns of the <hi>Parrades</hi> and Motions of the <hi>Leſſons,</hi> and then, and not till then (which will be about three Weeks, or a Month at moſt after his firſt entring) ſhould be given him a weighty <hi>Fleuret</hi> to ſtrengthen his <hi>Wreſt</hi> and <hi>Nerves,</hi> and with that he ſhould alwayes take his <hi>Leſſons,</hi> and <hi>Parrie</hi> his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries plain <hi>Thruſts</hi> at the wall, the uſing of which, will undoubtedly make him handle a light <hi>Fleuret</hi> or Sword, as he ſhall have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them, a great deal more firmly &amp; nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, then if he had alwayes uſed a light <hi>Fleuret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For (to make a Compariſon) as it is the Common Cuſtom for <hi>Dancing Maſters</hi> abroad, to wear plates of <hi>Leed</hi> betwixt the plies of the Soles of their Ordinary walking Shoes, that ſo they may ſeel themſelves as it were Lighter, and Cleevrer, when they put on their Light <hi>Dancing</hi> Shoes; ſo will the conſtant uſing of weighty <hi>Fleurets,</hi> make Men when they are to aſſault with Light ones, or to make uſe of their <hi>Sword,</hi> to think them a great deal Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then really they are, and the very Fancy of that will cauſe them make both, their <hi>Parrades,</hi> and <hi>Thruſts</hi> quicker then otherwayes they would; But, as I ſaid, their <hi>Wreſts</hi> ſhould be alwayes made Supple, and firſt accuſtomed with very Light <hi>Fleurets,</hi> untill they be three
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31657:40"/>Weeks or a Month at School, and then it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> time to give them heavy <hi>Fleurets</hi> to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir <hi>Leſſons</hi> withal and not ſooner, unleſs their Maſters deſigne to weaken and ruine their <hi>Wreſts</hi> and <hi>Nerves.</hi> And this Leads me to</p>
               <p>The Second thing I obſerve, is not ſo much Practiſed in our <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Schools</hi> as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould wiſh (for I acknowledge the <hi>French</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re free of it) which is the conſtant <hi>Parreing,</hi> and <hi>Thruſting</hi> of <hi>Plain Thruſts</hi> upon one another at the wall, this is the only thing which maketh a Man to have a Swift Hand upon his Purſute, and a firme and ſure <hi>Parrade</hi> upon his Defence, and there is no other Reaſon for the <hi>French</hi> their having ſo Swift a Hand in giving in their <hi>Plain Thruſts,</hi> but their conſtant accuſtoming themſelves to <hi>Thruſt</hi> upon their commarads at the Wall, or ſometimes at a Mark in the Wall, when they want the opportunity of having one to <hi>Thruſt</hi> upon; therefore ſeing the having a Swift Hand is of ſuch advantage, and the moſt certain way to acquire it, is, to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the <hi>Thruſting</hi> and <hi>Parreing</hi> of <hi>Plain Thruſts</hi> at the Wall, and that (as I have Orderd), with heavy <hi>Fleurets</hi> I think it will be thought but Reaſonable that I adviſe the Rectifying of this, as well as the preceeding abuſe.</p>
               <p>The Third thing I obſerve, is, that they burden their Scholars with too many <hi>Leſſons,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:31657:41"/>eſpecially <hi>Offenſive ones,</hi> whereas if they would teach them fewer <hi>Offenſive Leſsons</hi> (for they will come to them Naturally) and keep them cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the <hi>Defenſive</hi> Part, People would ſee fewer <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and better <hi>Sword-men</hi> in the Schools, then for the moſt Part they do.</p>
               <p>The fourth, is, the ſuffering Scholars general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take their <hi>Leſſons</hi> in their Cloaths, a thing which hindereth a Mans Body to be ſo ſoon broken, and made Pliable as otherwayes it would, becauſe a Man cannot ſtretch ſo freely in his Coat as he can do in a <hi>Weſt-coat,</hi> or <hi>Veſt,</hi> &amp; alſo it ſpoileth his Cloths, &amp; if he <hi>Fenceth</hi> much, the ſweat maketh him uneaſy the whole Day thereafter, whereas Playing in a <hi>Weſt-coat</hi> a Man is both Nimbler, and more at eaſe the reſt of the Day, his Coat being dry when he goeth from the School, which perhaps other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes would be all torn and neaſtie with the ſmell of Sweet and duſt, which would be both uneaſie to him, and unpleaſant to thoſe he is going to converſe with</p>
               <p>Therefore in my humble opinion no Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat ſhould be ſuffered to take his <hi>Leſſons</hi> in his Cloaths untill he be well Grounded, and then in oppoſition to what I have been ſaying, I am of the opinion that he ſhould for the moſt part both take his <hi>Leſſons,</hi> and <hi>Aſſault</hi> in his Cloaths and walking Shoes, for this will confirm him in his Play, and make him upon all Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:31657:41"/>ready, without being ſurprized, to oppoſe the Purſutes and Attaques of his Adverſary, with as great eaſe, as if he were ſtript and in his <hi>Fencing</hi> ſhoes, now this being of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to Compleat and Confirme a <hi>Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in his Play, it ſhould by all means be lookt to and taken notice of, that Schollars before they be well Grounded both in <hi>Leſſons</hi> and practice, do not Play in their Cloaths, and that afterwards when they are Grounded they ſhould, to ſtrengthen and confirm them in it</p>
               <p>The Fifth is the ſuffering Schollars ſo ſoon in <hi>Aſſault</hi> before they be at leaſt of two or three Months ſtanding, and this is alſo one of the Reaſons, why People ſee ſo many <hi>Contre-temps</hi> exchanged in the Schools, becauſe when they begin to <hi>Aſſault</hi> ſo ſoon, they have neither Art nor <hi>Judgement</hi> to ſhun or prevent them: and were it for no more but this, I think the Maſters ſhould rectifie it, that they would find it for their own particular Profit and Advantage; for when once their Schollars are accuſtomed to <hi>Aſſault,</hi> they think it almoſt below them to take any more <hi>Leſſons,</hi> but think they have attained enough of the <hi>Art,</hi> and ſo Quite the School, and there is an end of them, and by being at the School, they get the Name of <hi>Sword-men</hi> which is enough to them, but GOD knows, if they really deſerve it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31657:42"/>as if they were kept longer from <hi>Aſſaulting</hi> they would both continue longer their Scho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and at the end prove better <hi>Sword-men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sixth and laſt thing I ſhall take notic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of in <hi>Fencing</hi> Schools, is the neglect of teaching the <hi>Blow</hi> as well as the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and this both the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Maſters are guilty of, a well as our <hi>Scots;</hi> And I am apt to think it may proceed from a miſtake, in thinking that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teaching of the <hi>Blow</hi> would be prejudicial t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the quick performance of the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> but who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ever may be prepoſſeſt with this falſe Opini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on, I ſhall endeavour to convince them of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contrary by what followeth, and of the nece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity there is for a Mans being taught, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding both <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> to be reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Compleat <hi>Sword-man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the chief reaſons, or objections they give againſt teaching of the <hi>Blow, or Broad-ſword</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Small,</hi> are three; The firſt is, that it doth not teach a Man to ſtretch himſelf ſo much as the ſmall <hi>Sword</hi> doth, and therefore will not ſupple and break his Body ſo well, and conſequently not give him that agility of <hi>Wreſt</hi> and <hi>Limbs,</hi> which the <hi>Sm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sword</hi> doth.</p>
               <p>In anſwer to which I ſay firſt, that it is a great miſtake, to think that the <hi>Blow</hi> doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teach a Man to ſtretch, as well as the <hi>Thruſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:31657:42"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in Learning the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> there is nothing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aketh a Man to ſtretch, and to acquire nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leneſs and agility in his <hi>Limbs,</hi> but Advancing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eteiring, Elonging, and ſometimes Jumping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ack after the giving in of a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> now all this Man doth when he is taught the <hi>Blow,</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iad-ſword,</hi> and therefore there is no difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etwixt the learning of the <hi>Broad-ſword,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mall,</hi> for the acquiring of agility and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leneſs.</p>
               <p>I know ſome will ſay, that the chief difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſiſts in the <hi>Elonging,</hi> becauſe in learning the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al-ſword,</hi> a Man is taught <hi>to ſtretch himſelf a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eal more,</hi> then when he is learning the <hi>broad;</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k-ſword;</hi> but this is likewiſe a miſtake, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe who teach the true Art of the <hi>Broad-ſword,</hi> anſetheir <hi>Schollars</hi> when they take their <hi>Leſſons,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake their full <hi>Elonges</hi> or <hi>Stretches,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe recover, and jump backoff thoſe <hi>Stretches,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s frequently, as if they were taught the <hi>Smal,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe Maſters who teach not the <hi>Broad; or Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> after this manner, diſcover only their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ignorance, but no imperfection in the Art:</hi> and although I am fully perſwaded, that the <hi>Small-ſword</hi> hath the Advantage of the <hi>Broad,</hi> as to the quickneſs and ſubtility of its Motions; yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m convinced it hath no Advantage over it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to the rendring a Man more Agile and Nim-ble; And therefore that the teaching of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:31657:43"/>the <hi>Blow</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be no wayes prejudicial to the quick perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the <hi>Thruſt</hi> afterwards, as a man ſhall have occaſion for it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay the teaching of the <hi>Blow</hi> a the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> is not only as have made appear, no wayes prejudicial to a Mans ſtretching his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Limbs,</hi> but alſo doth not hinder him to acquire that agility and nimbleneſs of the <hi>Wreſt,</hi> which is required to have a ſwift Hand in the giving in of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Thruſt,</hi> for let any Man but conſider the turn of the <hi>Wreſt</hi> in making any of the <hi>Parrades,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> playing any of the <hi>Leſſons</hi> belonging to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Small-ſword,</hi> and the turns of it in performing the <hi>Blows</hi> and <hi>Flouriſhes</hi> of the <hi>Broad,</hi> and he will find the turns in the <hi>Broad</hi> to be a great dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more Circular and difficult, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fitter for the Suppling and Breaking of a Mans <hi>Wreſt,</hi> that ſo it may become Nimble and Agile, then any <hi>Parrade</hi> or <hi>Leſſon</hi> of the <hi>Smal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and there is no great Wonder it ſhould be ſo, ſeing it hath its Riſe and foundation from the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Broad,</hi> for I believe there are but few who are <hi>Ignorant</hi> of the antiquity of the <hi>Art</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Broad-ſword,</hi> and how that it was long made uſe of before ever the <hi>Small</hi> was found out, or heard of, and I am ſo far from think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Small-ſword</hi> a particular
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:31657:43"/>
                  <hi>Art</hi> by it ſelf, that I am fully convinced, it is only the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Broad</hi> more refined, and made more perfect, in ſo far as at firſt the <hi>Blow</hi> was only made uſe of without any <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Smal-ſword</hi> perfecteth it, by teaching how the <hi>Thruſt</hi> may be joyned to the <hi>Blow</hi> without any the leaſt confuſion, or hinderance, of the <hi>Blow,</hi> as occaſion ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Now how the teaching of both at one &amp; the ſame time hath run into deſuetude, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I cannot comprehend, but certainly it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eglect and omiſſion, which all who deſire to be compleat <hi>Sword-men,</hi> ſhould endeavour to have rectified.</p>
               <p>The Second objection is, that grant the teaching of the <hi>Blow</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> doth not hinder a Mans Stretching, or his acquiring the ſame agility of Body and nimbleneſs of <hi>Wreſt,</hi> which he would do if he were only taught the <hi>Small;</hi> yet ſay ſome, there is ſuch a vaſt difference betwixt the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a <hi>Blow,</hi> and the giving in of a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> that if a Man were taught to do them both at one time, the one would quite confound the other, and make a Man when he is taking his <hi>Leſſon</hi> with the <hi>Small,</hi> to give a <hi>Blow</hi> when he ſhould give a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and when he is tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Leſſon</hi> with the <hi>broad,</hi> to give in a <hi>Thruſt</hi> when he ſhould make a <hi>Blow,</hi> which would
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:31657:44"/>render both the <hi>Arts</hi> altogether uſeleſs to him; and therefore a Man had better perfect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf fully in the one, before he attempt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then deſire to be taught them both at one, and the ſame time</p>
               <p>Here is (one would think) a very ſtrong and reaſonable objection, but yet it ſhall be very clearly and ſhortly anſwered, and firſt, I ſay betwixt the <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> of the <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſword,</hi> and <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> of the <hi>Small,</hi> at leaſt the moſt part of them, there is but little Difference: for the <hi>Parrades</hi> in Quart and Terce of the <hi>Medium-guard,</hi> do reſemble the firſt <hi>Parrades</hi> in <hi>Quart</hi> and <hi>Terce</hi> of the <hi>Smal-ſword,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Parrads</hi> of the <hi>Hanging-guard,</hi> do likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the ſecond <hi>Parrades</hi> in <hi>Terce</hi> of the <hi>Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſword</hi> with a ſlooping point: thus much for the <hi>Parrades,</hi> and as for the <hi>Guards,</hi> the poſture of the <hi>Medium-guard</hi> is little Different from that of the <hi>Quart-guard</hi> in the <hi>Small,</hi> the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide-guard</hi> little different from the <hi>Terce,</hi> and the <hi>Hanging-guard</hi> little different from the <hi>Terce-guard</hi> in the <hi>Smal-ſword</hi> with a <hi>ſlooping point;</hi> ſo that the difference that are betwixt the <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>guards</hi> of the <hi>Small ſword,</hi> and <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> of the <hi>Broad</hi> are ſo inconſiderable, that I am confident no Man who underſtandeth both, will ſay, that the teaching the <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> of the one can be any ways Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:31657:44"/>to the teaching the <hi>Parrads</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> of the other at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>But Secondly if there be any conſiderable difference, it lieth in the offenſive part; in that, there is as they ſay, a vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the delivering of a <hi>Blow,</hi> and the giving in of a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and this is that which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain will ſo much Confound a Man that it will make him <hi>Strike</hi> when he ſhould <hi>Thruſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Thruſt</hi> when he ſhould <hi>Strike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part, I confeſs I cannot but admire how People of <hi>Judgement</hi> can talk at this rate, for can there be a greater Difference betwixt the performance of any <hi>Stroak,</hi> and the giving in of a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> then there is betwixt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of one <hi>Leſson</hi> in the <hi>Smal-ſword,</hi> and the <hi>Playing</hi> another in the ſame <hi>Art</hi> no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for there is as great, yea more Difference betwixt a <hi>Plain Thruſt,</hi> and <hi>Feinta la teſt,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Feint a la teſt,</hi> and <hi>Binding,</hi> or betwixt <hi>Binding</hi> &amp; <hi>Paſſing,</hi> or betwixt <hi>Paſſing</hi> and <hi>Quart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Volting,</hi> then there can be pretended to be betwixt the giving in of a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and the making of any <hi>Blow</hi> whatſomever, ſo that if upon the one Hand it be Pleaded that the Difference betwixt <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> is the Reaſon why they ſhould not be taught together, becauſe the one would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the other, I plead upon the other Hand
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:31657:45"/>and for the ſame Reaſon, that nothing ſhould be taught of the <hi>Small ſword</hi> at the ſame time but a <hi>Plain Thruſt,</hi> becauſe the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt it and the other <hi>Leſſons</hi> is as conſiderable, if not more; and therefore as apt to confound a Man, becauſe when he ſhould <hi>Play</hi> one <hi>Leſſon,</hi> he will make uſe of another as far out of purpoſe and ſeaſon, as the making of a <hi>Blow</hi> would be when he ſhould give a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> but all this is ſo ridiculous, that I ſhall ſay no more of it; for a Man who will maintain this, muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo maintain, that a Man cannot learn any two different Exerciſes at once, <hi>as for Ex:</hi> the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of the <hi>Pick</hi> and <hi>Musket,</hi> or to Play up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Guittar</hi> and <hi>Lute,</hi> or to <hi>Dance</hi> a <hi>Courant</hi> and <hi>Minue</hi> without confounding the one with the other, becauſe they have all Different Motions, which is a moſt extravagant opinion, and the contrary of which we ſee dayly practiſed not only by Men, but even by Beaſts; for I believe there are but few Gentlemen who have been abroad, and have not ſeen Horſes when they have been either Breaking for the Manage, or to confirm them in it, get moſt different <hi>Leſſons</hi> for that effect in one Morning, as one to ſupple their <hi>Shoulders,</hi> another to put them upon their <hi>Haunches,</hi> one for <hi>Paſsager,</hi> another for the <hi>Terra a Terra,</hi> one for <hi>Corvetting,</hi> another for <hi>Crouppading,</hi> and in fine, one for <hi>Caprioling,</hi> and another for <hi>Balotad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:31657:45"/>and all this (as I ſaid) in one Morning, now the motions of the Horſes limbs are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in all thoſe Leſſons and Aires, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the difference of the motions doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found an irrational Horſe, nor hinder him to perform what ever Leſſon or Aire his Rider requireth of him; I conclude, That the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> will far leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found or hinder a Rational Man to make uſe of either, as it ſhall pleaſe him, or his Maſter to demand them of him. But that <hi>I</hi> may the better both vindicate my Opinion as to this, and perſwade you, that it is not meerly a <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative fancy,</hi> but a moſt practicable, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full improvement of the <hi>Art of the Sword;</hi> I do recommend to all who ſhall not be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of it by the reaſonable Arguments I have propoſed, that they would Repair to <hi>William Machries School,</hi> where they will ſee both <hi>Blow &amp; Thruſt,</hi> taught at the ſame time with a great deal of eaſe and expedition, and without the leaſt confuſion.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt objection, is this, that ſuppoſing the Teaching of the <hi>Blow</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> be no ways prejudicial to the quick performance of the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and that all I ſaid in favours of the <hi>Blow</hi> ſhould hold good &amp; true, yet it is altogether unneceſſary to teach the <hi>Blow,</hi> becauſe a Man that is abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maſter of the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> can ſupply all the wants
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:31657:46"/>of the <hi>Blow</hi> by it, and ſeing the <hi>Thruſt</hi> hath ſo great Advantage over the <hi>Blow,</hi> as to the danger and deadlineſs of its wounds, which no <hi>Sword-man</hi> will deny, and that it can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be made uſe of in place of a <hi>Blow,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Teaching of the <hi>Blow</hi> is not neceſſary, but ought to be foreborn.</p>
               <p>You ſee by this objection they endeavour wholly to condemn and exclude the <hi>Blow,</hi> not as being any wayes prejudicial to the quick performance of the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> but as being, in it ſelf altogether uſeleſs, and not to be regarded, in reſpect of the Advantage the <hi>Small ſword</hi> hath of it, by the Dangerous Wounds it maketh, which prove, for the moſt part Mortall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as commonly the Wounds of the <hi>Broad-ſword</hi> are not ſo Dangerous, which in my Opinion inſinuats as much, as that a Man with a <hi>Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſword</hi> ſhould not ſtand to hazard his Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Blow</hi> for the giving of a <hi>Thruſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs I am as much convinced of the Advantage the <hi>Thruſt</hi> hath of the <hi>Blow</hi> as to it's Wound, as any Man can be, as you may ſee in my <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts Fencing-maſter;</hi> but that which I condemn is that an <hi>Arteſt</hi> ſhould truſt to the difference of Wounds, and ſo venture a <hi>Contre-temps,</hi> and not rather endeavour firſt to defend himſelf by his <hi>Art</hi> from the <hi>Blow,</hi> and then give in his <hi>Thruſt</hi> for a Man may chance to miſplant his <hi>Thruſt</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:31657:46"/>after he hath received a very ſevere Stroak, perhaps near to loſs of his Hand, and then I am confident, he will think it had been better <hi>Judgement,</hi> and he would have ſhewn more of his <hi>Art,</hi> if he had defended firſt the Stroak, and then have given in his <hi>Thruſt:</hi> but paſſing over this,</p>
               <p>I aſſure you there is no <hi>Smal-ſword-man,</hi> be he never ſo expert, but will find himſelf at a conſiderable Diſadvantage in offering to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend a Stroak, unleſs he particularly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſome thing of the defence of the <hi>Blow,</hi> or <hi>Broad ſword,</hi> and for my own part I found ſo great a Diſadvantage in not being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Blows</hi> of the <hi>Broad-ſword,</hi> when I had occaſion to Play with the <hi>Fleuret</hi> againſt the <hi>Cudgell,</hi> (for I was once al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of this opinion my ſelf) that I was never at caſe untill I found out a particular poſture for the <hi>Small-ſword</hi> againſt the <hi>Broad;</hi> which I did, and it is alſo ſet down in my <hi>Scots Fencing-Maſter,</hi> but my curioſity not reſting there I reſolved to learn a little of the <hi>Broad-ſword</hi> alſo, which I did in a very ſhort time, and ſince I find it a great deal more eaſy to me to defend my ſelf either with <hi>Broad</hi> againſt a <hi>Broad,</hi> or with a <hi>Small</hi> againſt a <hi>Broad,</hi> then I did at that time, and the reaſon is, becauſe I now know both the <hi>Parrades</hi> and <hi>Leſſons</hi> peculiar to the <hi>Broad,</hi> which before I was ignorant of,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:31657:47"/>and which put me to the trouble, as I ſaid, of finding out a particular poſture with the <hi>Smal-ſword</hi> for it, which did indeed at that time an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my deſign, but doth ſo now much more, becauſe I underſtand the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>Broad-ſword</hi> better now then I did then.</p>
               <p>I tell you this, not out of any Vanity to commend my ſelf, but that you may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what Advantage there is in being taught both <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and let any man who doubteth it, and hath only been taught to <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and to Defend a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> make but a trial, and I am confident he will find the ſame difficulty I did, and be ſoon of the ſame opinion I was when I wrot my other Book, to which I Refer him, and of which I am ſtill; <q>
                     <hi>That every Man who deſires to be a Compleat</hi> Sword-man <hi>ſhould Learn both</hi> Blow <hi>and</hi> Thruſt, <hi>and unleſs a Man do it I do not ſee how be can pretend to the Name of a Compleat</hi> Sword-man, <hi>for if a Man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand only the</hi> Thruſt <hi>and not the</hi> Blow, <hi>then he may deſerve the Name of a Compleat</hi> Small-ſword-man, <hi>but not of a Compleat</hi> Sword-man, <hi>becauſe he is</hi> Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>of the</hi> Blow.</q> In likemaner if a Man underſtand only the <hi>Blow</hi> and not the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> he may deſerve the Name of a Compleat <hi>Broad-ſword-man,</hi> but not of a Compleat <hi>Sword-man,</hi> becauſe he Underſtandeth not alſo the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> ſo that in my Opinion to deſerve the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:31657:47"/>name of a Compleat <hi>Sword-man,</hi> a Man muſt underſtand both <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> otherwiſe that Title doth no wayes belong to him, neither can he with any confidence pretend to it.</p>
               <p>But beſides what I have ſaid, there is no <hi>Sword-man</hi> will deny, but that it ſometimes ſo falleth out when Men are Playing together, that it would be more convenient to make a <hi>Blow</hi> then to give in a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and upon the other Hand, at other times more convenient to give in a <hi>Thruſt</hi> then to make a <hi>Blow,</hi> ſo that if a Man know not how to deliver a <hi>Blow</hi> as well as a <hi>Thruſt,</hi> he is upon theſe occaſions at a viſible loſs and diſadvantage, whereas if he knew how to perform both, he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes know how to behave himſelf according to theſe ſeveral circumſtances without the leaſt confuſion.</p>
               <p>But why need I in this Place endeavour to prove the neceſſity of that, the contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is condemned by the conſtant practice of moſt Nations in the World, for do we not ſee the generality of the People both Gentle and Simple, when they go to the Warrs, provide themſelves for the moſt part with <hi>ſheering-Swords,</hi> and why would they do that, if it were not out of an opinion, that they think they may have occaſion to <hi>Strike</hi> as well as to <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and that they think the <hi>Thruſt</hi> alone would not be ſo effectual, as when it can be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:31657:48"/>joined to the <hi>blow,</hi> and that they are, being thus provided, in a better capacity to make uſe of either at pleaſure, and accordingly as occaſion ſhall offer; From all which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That there is an abſolute neceſſity for a Man who intends to be a <hi>compleat Sword-man,</hi> to be taught and underſtand both <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and I think it a thing ſo indiſpenſably neceſſary, that the learning of it by all perſons who underſtand it not, whether Maſters or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, at all times, and at any Age whatſoever, can no ways reflect upon their <hi>Judgement</hi> in the Art they profeſs, nor be any wayes derogatory from the reputation they have already had of being good <hi>ſmall-Sword-Men,</hi> and the like I ſay in behalf of the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> to thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs only the <hi>Broad,</hi> ſo that I think neither of them ſhould think it below them to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of other, in what they are ignorant of, and of what is ſo uſeful and neceſſary for the compleat perfecting of the <hi>Art of the Sword,</hi> and conſequently of <hi>Sword-men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seing therefore (as I think I have ſufficiently made appear) there is an abſolute neceſſity for underſtanding both <hi>blow</hi> and <hi>thruſt</hi> to be reputed a <hi>compleat Sword-Man,</hi> I muſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the uſe of the <hi>Sheering-ſword,</hi> and I would adviſe all without exception, who wear now only <hi>Rapiers,</hi> to wear light and narrow <hi>Sheering-ſwords,</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:31657:48"/>at leaſt <hi>Rapiers</hi> with good-edges, which will both anſwer the deſign of the <hi>ſmall-ſword</hi> as to <hi>thruſting,</hi> and of the <hi>Broad</hi> as to the <hi>blow</hi> or <hi>ſtriking,</hi> and ſo put a Man in a capacity of uſing either as he ſhall think fit, when it ſhall be his misfortune to be engaged, and which will be as light and convenient to carry, as any ordinary <hi>walking-ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its like the <hi>Fencing-Maſters</hi> in this Kingdom may think I have gone too great a length upon this ſubject, in ſo far as I take upon me to play the Doctor, and offer as it were in a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterial way,</hi> to teach them their Duty, and alſo in that I ſeem to tax ſome of them of <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> in not underſtanding the <hi>blow</hi> as well as the <hi>thruſt,</hi> becauſe I recommend the learning of the <hi>blow</hi> to Maſters, if they be ignorant of it as well as to others.</p>
               <p>But that they may not miſtake me, I deſire they would conſider that this preceeding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (anent the abuſes in Schools) doth not particularly aim at them, but at all <hi>Fencing-Maſters</hi> in general, both at Home and Abroad, who are guilty of them; and that they are really guilty of them, I appeal to all who have frequented their Schools; therefore I expect our Maſters will not take what I have ſaid as a particular reflection upon them, although I cannot deny but they ſuffer the ſame abuſes to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:31657:49"/>be committed in their Schools; and therefore muſt excuſe me, if I cenſure them with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſters, untill I find them rectified.</p>
               <p>And let them not think it will paſs as a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon for them to continue theſe preceeding abuſes in their Schools, by ſaying it is the cuſtome abroad, and that they ſuffer nothing to be done in their Schools, but what is done in the Schools of other Kingdoms, and that becauſe it is not the cuſtome for any <hi>Small-ſword</hi> Maſter abroad to teach the <hi>Blow</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> that therefore they will not do it, becauſe they intend not to be the firſt Beginners and Promoters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any thing which is extraordinary and out faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which to my particular knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the chief Defence and Language of ſome) this I ſay is but very weak reaſoning, for at that rate there ſhould never have been any <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Science</hi> found out, or improven, if People had been alwayes reſtricted to the old Roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Footſteps of their Predeceſſors, ſo I expect they will either give me as ſtrong Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rectifying of theſe abuſes, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the teaching the <hi>Blow</hi> at the ſame time with the <hi>Thruſt</hi>) as I have given for them, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes they moſt pardon me to differ from them, by recommending my own opinion which is grounded upon reaſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning and Rejecting theirs at leaſt until
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:31657:49"/>they produce ſtronger Arguments and Reaſons for it, then hitherto I have heard.</p>
               <p>And although this indeed be my Opinion, that <hi>Ignorant</hi> Maſters who underſtand not the <hi>Blow,</hi> ſhould learn it; yet it doth not conclude that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reckon thoſe who profeſs the <hi>Art</hi> of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>word</hi> in this Kingdom to be in that Categorie, no, I am farr from having ſo bad an Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, and I am apt to think the only thing they ſhould be condemned for, and for which I do indeed condemn them, is not that they underſtand not the <hi>Blow</hi> as well as the <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and therefore are not capable to reach it (for if they denied that, they would diſcover too much weakneſs) but that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding both, ſhould teach only the one, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Thruſt,</hi> and wholly neglect the other, by throwing it our of Doors, this I confeſs is a neglect of ſuch importance, and of ſuch bad conſequence, that I neither can, nor will fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear the giving my earneſt advice, that it, as well as the five preceeding particulars, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectified, and then I am confident our Schollars <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall acquire <hi>Art</hi> inferior to none in <hi>Europe,</hi> and our Maſters, by them that repute and Eſteem, which both their abilities, and they, recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying of ſuch Abuſes, and Omiſſions, do really <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſerve.</p>
               <p>And I likeways would not have them ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:31657:50"/>Fooliſh as to think, that (by what I have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaying in Reference to the teaching both <hi>Blow</hi> and <hi>Thruſt</hi>) I deſign to recommend any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Maſter before another, no, I am not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mean as to have any ſuch Particular by-end my deſigne is ſo farr from that, that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together general, and meerly for the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>Art,</hi> and to Compleat <hi>Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> for if Maſters cannot by the <hi>Art,</hi> Care, and Pains they take, recommend themſelves t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Schollars, they ſhall never have any from me, becauſe I think all Maſters ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> puted, and had in Eſteem, only for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtinct and accurate method of teaching, and for the pains they take to cauſe their Scholla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> underſtand, and comprehend what they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Learning, and not for any recommendatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they can get from any Particular Perſon what ſomever, and therefore if they expect any particular recommendation from me, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hugely deceived, for I wiſh them all alike well that is to have Flouriſhing Schools, and E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Schollars, to teſtifie that they are Maſter indeed, and not Bunglers, of which there a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but too many.</p>
               <p>The next thing I obſerve, is, that if all I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid be duely and exactly put in practice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will infallibly make a Man a true <hi>Artiſt,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if he be truely an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> his having <hi>Art</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:31657:50"/>increaſe his boldneſs and courage, and put him in a capacity, not only to preſerve his Life and Honour, but alſo to force as it were a reſpect and eſteem to himſelf, from thoſe, who although they undervalue his <hi>Art,</hi> yet darr not be ſo bold (leaſt he ſhould make them ſmart for it) as publickly to own it, but are rather ſatisfied by their ſilence to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his dexterity, and that he is to be commended for the pains, and labour, he hath taken to acquire ſo gentile and uſeful an Art.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe they ſhould openly reflect upon him, and undervalue his Art, by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him with that unanſwerable defence, as they think of their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and infallible Defeater of all Art (I mean by ingaging him to fight with Piſtol, or other ſuch like Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weapons) and indeed to hear ſome People talk, one would think that by their gaming this one point, of engaging a <hi>Sword-man</hi> to ſight with Fire-armes, they make no doubt, but all will go well with them, and that the day is certainly their own, it being a kind of Proverb amongſt them. <q>
                     <hi>Is ſuch a Perſon a</hi> Sword-man, <hi>if it be anſwered, Yes, then reply they after a mocking manner; What doth it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſie? If I were to engage with him, I could ſoon make his Art of little uſe to him; I would take a Piſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him, and then I pray you where is all his
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:31657:51"/>Art of Defence, I believe he will hardly parie a Piſtol Ball with it.</hi>
                  </q> Such diſcourſe as this is but too common amongſt <hi>Ignorants,</hi> and they think when they talk at this rate, they have found the <hi>Philoſopher ſtone,</hi> which in place of turning every thing into Gold, can turn all their <hi>Ignorance</hi> into the profoundeſt Art and Skill, and all skilful Perſons, <hi>Art,</hi> and <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> into the greateſt <hi>Ignorance;</hi> ſo that in their opinion, <hi>Artiſts</hi> can reap no advantage by what they underſtand, and themſelves can reap all, becauſe they underſtand nothing.</p>
               <p>But alas poor <hi>Ignorants!</hi> Their Folly in this is as diſcernable, as their <hi>Ignorance</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and they can pretend to have no more Advantage over a <hi>Sword-man,</hi> by engaging him to make uſe of a Piſtol, then the <hi>Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> can pretend to have over them, which I ſhall endeavour to prove by what followeth.</p>
               <p>Although then I confeſs, that there is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly no Defenſive part in uſing of Piſtols, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Foot or upon Horſe-back, but what all Men are alike Maſter of, I mean to receive the ſhot, and take their hazard of being hit or miſt; for no Man will be ſo fooliſh, as to pretend to parie the ſhot of a Piſtol; yet there, are ſome methods, which I think not fit at preſent to mention, that may be uſed to ſhun a ſhot, the which who can neatly make uſe of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:31657:51"/>them, will certainly have an advantage of thoſe who underſtand them not, but ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up like an immovable ſtock or poſt, to be ſhot at.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing all Men alike dextrous as to this point, that is to know no means of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oiding, but meerly to take their hazard of being hit or not; yet I ſay, in the Offenſive part, there may be a vaſt Advantage acquired; for whoſoever will according to the advice in my <hi>Scots Fencing-maſter,</hi> accuſtom himſelf to ſhot at a Mark, both a Foot and on Horſe-back, will, when he is neceſſitate to uſe it in earneſt, have almoſt as conſiderable advantage over his Adverſary in knowing to adjuſt his ſhot, (ſuppoſing his Adverſary to be ignorant and not to have practiſed to adjuſt his) as he would have had a Foot in adjuſting his Thruſt, his Adverſary being likewiſe ignorant of the Art of the <hi>Sword;</hi> ſo that if this Perſon of whom I am diſcourſing, and who boaſteth ſo much of the Advantage he will have by uſing <hi>Piſtols,</hi> hath but as little of the practiſe of <hi>ſhooting,</hi> as he hath of <hi>Thruſting,</hi> he can then in Reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to no more Advantage by uſing the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol,</hi> then the <hi>Artiſt</hi> can, except what meer Chance and Fortune giveth him, which is far from any ground of certainty.</p>
               <p>Therefore, I ſay, he only will probably have
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:31657:52"/>the Advantage with <hi>Piſtol,</hi> who hath frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt the ſhooting at a Mark, and if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them have done that, then none of them can pretend to any viſible Advantage over the other; but what, as I ſaid, is meerly caſual and by chance. But I confeſs, if the <hi>Ignorant</hi> be better skill'd in <hi>ſhooting</hi> then the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> in that caſe he hath an Advantage; and I can ſee no Reaſon why the <hi>Artiſt</hi> ſhould more anſwer the Challenge with <hi>Piſtols,</hi> ſeing he is a better Marks-Man then the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> then he would anſwer the <hi>Artiſt</hi> with <hi>Swords,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Artiſt</hi> was the moſt Adroit at <hi>thruſting;</hi> So that the only way to end this Debate, is, that they either fight with Weapons altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unknown to both, or otherwiſe do as one of thoſe two Men, who after they had quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, leſt the one ſhould have had any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by Art in the Weapons which might have been made uſe of, did propoſe a Barrel of Gun-powder ſhould be brought to each, in the middle of which, they were to place themſelves, and then with fired Matches to try who could moſt Manfully, or I may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay Madly, blow up other. And I know no other way but this to decide the Quarrel: For if a Man refuſe to fight me with a Sword, becauſe he thinketh I am a better <hi>Sword-man</hi> than he, I muſt certainly be a great Fool, if I fight him with a <hi>Piſtol,</hi> becauſe he propoſeth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:31657:52"/>it as a particular Advantage to himſelf:</p>
               <p>I know it will be Anſwered to this, That it is the cuſtome for thoſe who receive the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, to chooſe the Weapons, and ſo that will end the Debate, becauſe who ever giveth the Challenge, is in Honour obliged to Anſwer the other with whatever Weapons he ſhall propoſe.</p>
               <p>I confeſs it is ſo, and I think it moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable when a Man is forced to fight, that he ſhould have the choice of what Weapon he will venture his Life with; But what I was ſaying, concerns only ſuch, for ſome, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have given a Challenge, and their Antagoniſt received it, and appointed <hi>Swords</hi> to be their Weapons, they afterwards getting notice that he is a <hi>Sword-man,</hi> cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the fighting him with that Weapon, and propoſe <hi>Piſtols,</hi> becauſe of the inequality there would be in making uſe of <hi>Swords.</hi> Now I ſay, when a <hi>Sword-man</hi> rancounters with ſuch a Perſon as this, who firſt giveth him a Challenge, &amp; then afterwards declines to fight him with the Weapons he propoſed, I ſee, I ſay, no reaſon why he ſhould more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him with <hi>Piſtols,</hi> ſeing he propoſed it for a particular Advantage, then the other did him with <hi>Swords,</hi> becauſe he judged it would prove to his diſadvantage; for if the Refuſal
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:31657:53"/>reflect upon any of the two, it muſt be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly upon him who gave the Challenge; Becauſe, although he was ſo ſtout as to Appeal, yet had not the Courage to Anſwer the other with the Weapons he propoſed; Therefore I conclude, That a man had far better forbear a Challenge, then decline the Weapons after they are choſen.</p>
               <p>But, There is in my humble Opinion, no better way to take away all ſuch Debates, then to live ſoberly and peaceably, according to the Doctrine and Precepts of that Religion which we profeſs, and then we ſhall make uſe of all thoſe Arts, more for divertiſement to ourſelves, then prejudice to our Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Now after what I have ſaid, let any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſon judge, if an <hi>ignorant,</hi> by ingaging a <hi>Sword-man</hi> to fight with a <hi>Piſtol,</hi> hath got ſo great an Advantage, as to be any wayes a ground of railing at, mocking, or turning into Ridicule the <hi>Art of the Sword,</hi> no certainly, he hath got none, but what the <hi>Artiſt</hi> may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe pretend to as well as he; and therefore I would adviſe ſuch Perſons rather to betake themſelves to the practice of <hi>Fencing,</hi> and <hi>Shot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing,</hi> that ſo their Advantage may be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and depend upon their Art, and not upon ſuch Fancies and Notions, which, if real, are caſual; but for the moſt part, prove Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:31657:53"/>and have only their exiſtence in their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorant Brains;</hi> but are below the being regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or taken notice of by any Gentleman or Judicious Perſon, who ſhould ground his thoughts upon Reaſon, and not in the Air; that if they be examined they may prove ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id and durable as Reaſon, and not volatile and changeable, as the Aerial Foundation upon which they are built, and ſo diſcover the Weakneſs and Ignorance of their firſt Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Author; But not to inſiſt longer upon this,</p>
               <p>I obſerve in the fourth and laſt place, that although all I have ſaid in commendation of <hi>Fencing,</hi> were but Stories and Lies, and the vain imaginations of a <hi>Hypocondriack—brain,</hi> yet all <hi>Gentlemen</hi> ſhould practiſe it, &amp; have an eſteem for it, if it were for no other reaſon but this, that it is a moſt pleaſant divertiſement, and an innocent, Healthful, and Manly Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Exerciſe for the Body, and although a Man could reap no Advantage by it for the Defence of his Body; yet that its very keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Mans joynts and members nimble and cleaver, and in a ready trime, as it were, for any other Divertiſement or Exerciſe, as Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice, Dancing, Riding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould make it Eſteemed and Practiſed by all who are above the rank of Clowns.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:31657:54"/>
               <p>For to uſe the words of a Wiſe-man, <q>
                     <hi>The underſtanding of this Noble and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Art, is a Quality and Perfection, hardly attainable by thoſe who hold the Plough, and glory in the Goad; who drive Oxen, and are occupied in their Labours, and whoſe talk is of their Bullocks, who give their mind to make Furrows; and are diligent to give the Kine fodder. No, it agreeth not with the Nature of ſuch; neither is it for the Smith who ſitteth by the Anvil, and conſidereth the Iron work, the vapour of the Fire, waſteth his Fleſh, and he figheth with the heat of the Furnace; the noiſe of the Hammer and Anvil is ever in his Ears, and his Eyes look ſtill upon the Patern of the thing he maketh.</hi>
                  </q> Such vulgar and undiſciplined Minds as thoſe, are not ordinarly capable to conceive the Intricacies, and Excellencies, of this moſt <hi>Gentile</hi> and <hi>Gentle-manny Art.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although it cannot be denied, but ſome mean kind of People profeſs, practiſe and take delight in it; yet thoſe are Men who are more refined in their Judgements and Inclinations, then the generality of the Vulgar are, and who by the ſame gentile Inclination they have to follow the Sword, diſcover that there is in them ſomething more then ordinary, and that they aime at ſomewhat, above what ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Birth or Education could really make them pretend to; ſo that I make no
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:31657:54"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oubt, but if ſuch Perſons had either really <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een, or had had the Education peculiar to Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-men, they would have been in a fitter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pacity both to have improven themſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd better inſtructed others in that Art, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich they have ſuch a reſpect and liking.</p>
               <p>And if this which I ſay hold true, then no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oubt but the underſtanding of this Art, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngeth in a more particular manner to Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, or thoſe who are called <hi>Les Hommes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſpee,</hi> then to any other; and therefore it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny advice, and I earneſtly recommend it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch, not to ungentleman themſelves by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eglect and contempt of an Art, which as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave made appear, is ſo peculiar to, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay ſay inſeparable from the Name and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haracter they bear.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An Art ſo Noble, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful, and Gentile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſpeak its praiſes, would a Volume fill;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For when that I, its Merits would diſplay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Mouth is ſtopt, my Muſe is at a ſtay.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It ſo exceeds all that I can conceive,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'm forc'd to ſilence, yet to ſpeak muſt crave;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſeing all I can expreſs and ſhew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Would far come ſhort, of what's its real due,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ſhall be ſhort, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of it ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is a Badge, Accompliſhment, and Ray,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which doth adorn all who to underſtand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:31657:55"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Its real <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Worth, do take in hand.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An Art ſo uſeful, that no Gentleman,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Valour, Honour, be without it can,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For it to all who carry Sword by ſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Should be a Pilot, and a conſtant Guide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs they do renounce the Name they bear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And that which them from others Character:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For my part, I confeſs I it eſteem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And for my truſty Safe-guard do it deem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And alwayes will, knowing it ne're deceives,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Any who to it truſt and reſpect gives;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But believe me who deſpiſe it wholly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ignorance <hi>betray, as well as Folly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And will repent them (when it is too late)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They truſted none to it, ſo much, to Fate.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>I confeſs I am neither <hi>Poet</hi> nor <hi>Verſificator,</hi> yet thoſe Lines offering to my Fancy, and relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Subject, I thought fit to ſet them down; if they are good its by chance, if not, paſs them over; I wrote them for my divertiſement, and its like had it not been to divert me, I had not taken the pains to write ſo much either of <hi>Fencing,</hi> or in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of it as I have done; However what I have Writ, I recommend to your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal, which I think can hardly be refuſed, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it coſt me a great deal of more pains in Writting, then it will do you in Reading; and if you deſpiſe my offer, I aſſure you, I ſhall
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:31657:55"/>take it ſo ill, and be ſo much concerned, that I ſhall never ſleep a whit the worſe for it.</p>
               <p>But that I may draw to a cloſe, if any who ſhall peruſe this Diſcourſe, do not underſtand the Terms of Art herein mentioned, ſuch as <hi>Contre-caveating-Parrades, Contre-temps, Flanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude, Voult-coupee, &amp;c.</hi> They may have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to my Book of <hi>Fencing,</hi> Entituled, <hi>The Scots Fencing-Maſter,</hi> where they will find all theſe Termes and Leſſons explained to the full.</p>
               <p>And that I may end as I began, I earneſtly entreat and deſire, that with <hi>Calmneſs,</hi> and a <hi>Vigorous Judgement,</hi> you would ſeriouſly reflect upon, and conſider what I have ſaid, before you paſs your Verdict and Opinion, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doubt not, but it ſhall jump very near with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y own, which is what I expected and wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>ADIEU.</salute>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:31657:56"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:31657:56"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
